<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The ioy of Ierusalem and woe of the worldlings. A sermon preached at Pauls Crosse the 18. of Iune. 1609. By William Loe Batcheler of Diuinity.</title>
            <author>Loe, William, d. 1645.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1609</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 116 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 66 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A68403</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 16685</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S102897</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99838659</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99838659</idno>
            <idno type="VID">3045</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A68403)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 3045)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 673:14, 844:05)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The ioy of Ierusalem and woe of the worldlings. A sermon preached at Pauls Crosse the 18. of Iune. 1609. By William Loe Batcheler of Diuinity.</title>
                  <author>Loe, William, d. 1645.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[126] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T. Haueland for C. Knight and I. Harrison, and are to be sold [by C. Knight] in Pauls Church-yard at the signe of the holy Lambe,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1609.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Bookseller's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-H (-H1).</note>
                  <note>A variant; includes "and prebendarie of the Cathedrall Church of Glocester" following "Batcheler of Diuinity" in title, and 2 leaves ([par.1,2] of dedication after leaf A1.</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 16685c on UMI microfilm reel 673.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
                  <note>Appears at reel 673 þ, and at reel 844 #5 (Folger Shakespeare Library copy filmed twice).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-03</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:3045:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3045:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Ioy of IERVSALEM: AND <hi>Woe of the Worldlings.</hi> A Sermon preached at <hi>Pauls Croſſe the 18. of</hi> IVNE. 1609.</p>
            <p>By WILLIAM LOE Batchelor of Diuinity.</p>
            <p>LONDON Printed by <hi>T. Haueland</hi> for <hi>C. Knight</hi> and <hi>I. Harriſon,</hi> and are to be ſold in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard at the ſigne of the holy Lambe. 1609.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:3045:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3045:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A SERMON <hi>Preached at</hi> PAVLS <hi>Croſſe</hi> the eighteenth of <hi>Iune.</hi> 1609.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>IOHN 17. 9.</bibl>
               <q>I pray for them: I pray not for the world, but for them which thou haſt gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen me; for they are thine.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hat the Almightie God purpoſed in <hi>Dauid</hi> the fathers heart, hee perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in <hi>Salomon</hi> the ſonnes hand. <hi>Dauid</hi> voweth, his head ſhall take no reſt, nor his<note place="margin">Pſal. 132.</note> temples any repoſe, vntill he had found out an habitation for the God of <hi>Iacob.</hi> This proiect was perfected by <hi>Salomon,</hi> who built
<pb facs="tcp:3045:3"/>
the Temple; and hauing built it, conſecrates and dedicates it with<note place="margin">1. Reg. 8.</note> praier and praiſe vnto <hi>Iohouah.</hi> God the Father, in the ſecret cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell of his heauenly Conſiſtorie, chuſeth a myſticall Temple vnto himſelfe, the erecting wherof was manifeſted in his ſonne Chriſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus. <hi>Dauid</hi> vow and purpoſe, a fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure of God the Fathers election and preordinate counſell: <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons</hi> performance, and erection of the Temple, a type of Chriſt Ieſus declaration, ful accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the promiſes, and perfect demonſtration of the predeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate will of his heauenly Fathers ſecret purpoſe. So that, what was <hi>Propoſitum</hi> in God the Father, is <hi>Depoſitum</hi> in Ieſus Chriſt the ſon,<note place="margin">2. Tim<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 4. 8</note> and <hi>Repoſitum</hi> in expectation of the faithfull, <hi>quibus imponetur,</hi> in that glorious day of his gratious
<pb facs="tcp:3045:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
doome. Behold now then, O yee Chriſtian people (bleſſed and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued in Ieſus Chriſt; for I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not giue you a more honourable title, be you honourable or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, if I ſhould giue you tenne thouſand) behold (I ſay) your re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all and royall <hi>Salomon,</hi> dedicating this myſticall and ſpirituall tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple with praier and praiſe vnto his righteous father, as in this whole Chapter it appeareth, wherein he praieth, firſt, for himſelfe; ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, for his Diſciples; thirdly, for all the elect. And not onelie praieth, but alſo as a iudicious <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon,</hi> vttereth that abſolute and moſt wiſe deſignation and diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, by way of prophecie, of theſe different generations (the bleſſed and curſed) which the wombe of this wretched world bringeth forth; and being in the
<pb facs="tcp:3045:4"/>
world, are not onely diuers, but contrarie in their actions, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections.</p>
            <p>He praieth, and praieth not. 1.<note place="margin">The diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</note> 
               <hi>I pray for them. 2. I pray not for the world.</hi> In his praying foure things remarkeable. 1. The perſon, <hi>I.</hi> 2. The pious and powerfull practiſe, <hi>I pray.</hi> 3. The parties deſigned, (<hi>for them.</hi>) 2. diſtinguſhed, (<hi>but for them.</hi>) 4. The reaſons why he prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth being two. 1. <hi>Donatiue, (which thou hast giuen me.) 2. Poſſeſsiue, (for they are thine.</hi>) In the perſon, 2. things obſeruable. 1. <hi>His name.</hi> 2<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> his <hi>Nature.</hi> In the pious practiſe, two things alſo. 1. The power of praier in others. 2. The peculiar propertie therof in him, in whom all other had their power. In the parties. 1. We will conſider their deſignement by the titles of fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uor &amp; honour ſet down in holie
<pb facs="tcp:3045:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
ſcripture. <hi>For them:</hi> that is, <hi>who are my Sons &amp; my Saints: my Princes &amp; my prieſts: my beloued &amp; my Baptized mine illuminates, &amp; mine Aſſociates.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 87. 3.</note> 
               <hi>For theſe glorious things are ſpoken, as of the citie: ſo of the Citizens of God.</hi> Secondly in the parties diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhment, or ſeparation, (<hi>but for them:</hi>) diſcerned and notified fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the world by three inſeparable notes, and remarkeable tokens of diſtinction. 1. <hi>A Catholike faith towards God. 2. Newnes of life in themſelues. 3. Euangelicall charitie towards others.</hi> In the reaſons. 1. Conſider the donation, how wee are giuen vnto Chriſt by God the father (<hi>which thou haſt giuen me:</hi>) that is, to be my ſeruants <hi>In foure ſeuered and ſingular ſuits and ſerui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.</hi> 1. In religious deuotion to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward God. 2. In zealous affection toward our brethren. 3. In humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie.
<pb facs="tcp:3045:5"/>
4. In bearing the Croſſe. 2. Conſider the poſſeſſion, how we are the fathers (<hi>for they are thin</hi>) euen thy Saints, whether we looke backwards, or forwards. Back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, thine they are. 1 By <hi>Election.</hi> 2. By <hi>Creation.</hi> Forwards, they are thine. 1 By <hi>Sanctification.</hi> 2. By <hi>Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rification.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the ſecond generall part, <hi>I pray not;</hi> Three things memorable. 1. The perſon <hi>I.</hi> 2. The excepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>I pray not.</hi> 3<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> The <hi>deſignation, for the world.</hi> In the perſon, his offices are to bee conſidered; as hee is a king, Prieſt, and Prophet: and how in euery of theſe, it is conſonant to his perſon and office that he doth not pray: wherein the obiections ſhall be anſwered, &amp; the text clee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. 2. In the acception, we will attend the reuealed reaſons why he praieth not for the world. And
<pb facs="tcp:3045:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
laſtlie in the <hi>Deſignation,</hi> let vs marke. 1. who are deſined by the world. 2. Why they are ſo deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed; and in concluſion take a ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uey of this preſent age, and world wherein we liue: which I feare, vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the view, wil appeare vnto vs to be that world, &amp; thoſe world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings that Chriſt prayed not for.</p>
            <p>But let vs return to the firſt ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral head, <hi>his praying:</hi> whereunto I earneſtly deſire you to attend as to one of the <hi>Songs</hi> of <hi>Sion,</hi> and the <hi>Ioy of Ieruſalem:</hi> and therein I ſhall pray you to watch and wait the firſt houre, to the ioy of your hearts, who truely ſeeke, and ſerue the Lord. As for the ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d houre, the woe of the worldlings (<hi>his not praying</hi>) ſhall bee denounced, that all fleſh may tremble, and all peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple perceiue the glorious ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of our God, and bee reſolued
<pb facs="tcp:3045:6"/>
why the world is ſo wicked, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly becauſe Chriſt praieth not for it.</p>
            <p>Firſt of the perſon. Many haue praied and not obtained: but now I pray ſaith Chriſt, whoſe name is <hi>Saluation,</hi> and whoſe power is <hi>ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> my name is <hi>Saluation,</hi> an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel<note place="margin">Mat. 1. 21.</note> ſpake it. <hi>Thou ſhalt cal his name Ieſus;</hi> the reaſon being added, <hi>for he ſhall ſaue his people from their ſins.</hi> From which Angelical aſſertion, the Diſciples conclude an <hi>Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licall:</hi> and peremptorie corallarie: <hi>There is ſaluation in no other</hi> (neither Pope nor Prieſt, <hi>Principalitie,</hi> nor power) <hi>for among men there is no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 4. 12.</note> 
               <hi>name giuen vnder heauen wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by wee muſt bee ſaued.</hi> My power alſo is ſafetie, for <hi>who ſo delighteth in the ſecret of the moſt high, ſhall a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide in the ſhadow of the Almightie.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 91. 1.</note> Neither is this <hi>Saluation</hi> tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rarie,
<pb facs="tcp:3045:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
as that of <hi>Sampſon</hi> or <hi>Sam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar, Gideon</hi> or <hi>Iepthah,</hi> but I am a <hi>Sauiour once for euer, I alone</hi> for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerie one, both effectually, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternallie.</p>
            <p>The vſe of this is; that wee muſt inuocate this name onely, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerence this power: this name be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our citie of refuge. <hi>The name</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 18. 10.</note> 
               <hi>of the Lord is a ſtrong tower, the righ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teous runne vnto it, and are ſecured.</hi> This power beeing our flag of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiance againſt the Lords, and our enemies; Faithfull <hi>Dauid</hi> being a fruitfull preſident in this reſolute direction. <hi>All nations compaſſed me about, but in the name of the Lord</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſ. 118. 10 11. 12<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> 
               <hi>I ſhall deſtroy them. They compaſſed mee againe, and againe: but in the name of the Lord I ſhal deſtroy them: yea, when they came and ſwarmed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout me like Bees, they are quenched as a fire of Thornes that choaketh them;</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:3045:7"/>
               <hi>for in the name of the Lord I ſhall deſtroy them. I pray,</hi> that haue both a Deuine, and humane nature. A diuine nature, to help, and a hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane to commiſerate and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dole therein, hauing a ſimpathy of our miſerie, and moane I came out of the land of the liuing; to bring you happines that ſit in the ſhadow of death. I bring you rich promiſes, and precious of the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie and grace of God the father, whereby you are alſo made par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers<note place="margin">2. Pet. 1. 4</note> of that heauenly nature, not in ſubſtance, as <hi>Seruetus</hi> groſſely i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>magined, but in qualitie, whether therfore you reſpect my name, or my nature, ſaith Chriſt, I am both willing, and able to ſuccour, and ſaue them that ſeeke mee. Onelie this you muſt dulie remember, that your glorious name of <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians,</hi> auaileth not, vnleſſe you bee
<pb facs="tcp:3045:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>
alſo partakers of the gratious na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: for euerie one that <hi>calleth on</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Tim. 2. 19.</note> 
               <hi>the name of Chriſt muſt depart from iniquitie.</hi> And thus much of the perſon. Now let vs goe on to the pious practiſe.</p>
            <p>Secondlie <hi>I pray.</hi> He praieth as a man: hee giueth as a God: ſaith Saint <hi>Auguſtine vpon this place.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Auguſt. in Iohan.</note> Much might here bee ſaid of prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and not to much: for it is the pretious Iewell, and peereleſſe pearle of our chriſtian profeſſion: but I tie my ſelfe to my parts pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, to wit, to ſhew the power thereof in others, and the ſpeciall propertie in him, by whom, and through whom, others had, and haue their power. The power of praier in others, both in the old Teſtament, and in the new, is as myraculous as marueilous. In the old, <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron</hi> are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
<pb facs="tcp:3045:8"/>
vpon by <hi>Pharaoh</hi> a reprobate, at that time when the plagues &amp; puniſhments of God lay vppon him, and his people, that they ſhould pray vnto their God for him, and their praiers were the meanes to take away, and eaſe thoſe diſtreſſed people fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thoſe vexations, &amp; torments. No char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of his fanatical Enchanters, no violence of his deſperate ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, no magnifience of his vaine Pyramides, although aduanced to heauen, could ought preuaile, but prayer onely: yea, powerfull praier in the Faith of Gods ſeruants,<note place="margin">Exod. 8. 9.</note> ſtands in the gap, and turnes away the plagues euen from <hi>Aegipt.</hi> It rained not in three yeares and a halfe, and the praier of <hi>Elias</hi> ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth<note place="margin">1. Reg. 18.</note> the buckets of heauen, lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth the bands of <hi>Orion,</hi> and the bottles of the clouds, as <hi>Iob</hi> calleth
<pb facs="tcp:3045:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>
them, when no other re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medie nor means could be found vnder heauen. A ſeelie and diſtreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, yet faithfull woman, <hi>Anna</hi> the Mother of <hi>Samuel,</hi> openeth not<note place="margin">1 Sam. 1.</note> her mouth in <hi>vocal</hi> praier, but in mental eleuation vnto her God, &amp; ſhe obtaineth the deſire of her heart; euen a Sonne at the hands of God, when as <hi>Ely</hi> the Prieſt i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>magined ſhee had beene drunke, and rebuked her, but ſhe yet con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued in her earneſt and power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full petition, and preuailed.</p>
            <p>In the new Teſtament alſo, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother reprobate <hi>Simon Magus,</hi> paraleling <hi>Pharaoh</hi> in the old, had this knowledge of the power of praier; That when <hi>Peter</hi> had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced againſt him the fearefull threats of Gods iudgements; Oh ſaith he, <hi>Pray you to the Lord for me,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 8. 24</note> 
               <hi>that none of theſe thinges which you</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:3045:9"/>
               <hi>haue ſpoken, come vppon mee.</hi> See, <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Magus</hi> went thus far in religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that he knew there was no ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier harbinger of truſt, could bee ſent to ſtay and ſtop the paſſage of thoſe fearefull plagues, but the Praier of Gods ſeruants. <hi>Peter</hi> is caught; put in priſon; deliuered to foure quaternions of <hi>Souldiers,</hi> by mightie and malitious <hi>Herod.</hi> He ſleepeth betweene two ſouldiers, bound with chaines, the keepers before the doore, yea, the verie night before hee ſhould bee brought foorth to the people. What meanes is there now for <hi>Peter</hi> to eſcape? Behold the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of praier; <hi>Earneſt praier</hi> was<note place="margin">Act. 12.</note> made of the <hi>church to God</hi> for him, ſaith the Scripture. This ſo pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaileth, that it procureth an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell to bee ſent from heauen: chaines cannot detaine him, nor
<pb facs="tcp:3045:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Priſon, nor Souldiers co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fine him: nor keepers reſtraine him: nor the Iron gate of the city ſtay him, but it openeth of it owne accord, and <hi>Peter</hi> is brought ſafe to his friends. Maruellous art thou O Lord, and glorious in thy works, but aboue all in thy mercie which thou ſheweſt vs in the priuile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deges<note place="margin">Act. 4<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 31.</note> of thy Church and choſen. The Apoſtles being ioyned toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in heartie and holie prayer, the verie place where they were aſſembled ſhooke, and trembled, for the maieſtie of Gods preſence was there. Conſider then that the verie earth whereon we liue and mooue, quakes at the powerfull operation of praier.</p>
            <p>If then praier bee ſo powerfull in thoſe who had their power by <hi>Chriſt,</hi> who heere praieth; How much more powerfull and preti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
<pb facs="tcp:3045:10"/>
is his praier? who is ſo gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious with God his Father, that a voice was heard from heauen ſaying, <hi>This is my welbeloued Sonne</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matt. 3. 17</note> 
               <hi>in whome I am well pleaſed.</hi> And a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, a ſecond time a voice from heauen anſwereth, <hi>I haue glorified</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 12. 28</note> 
               <hi>it, and I will glorifie it againe,</hi> when as the people that ſtood by, thought it had thundred. Yea, and an Angel is ſent from heauen<note place="margin">Luk. 22. 43</note> to comfort him, when hee was to enter into that great and gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous conflict of his bloodie ago<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie: yea, right powerfull muſt his praier be, that was iuſtified euen<note place="margin">Mat. 27. 19 24</note> by his enemies. <hi>Pilates</hi> wife wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth, <hi>Haue nothing to doe with that iuſt man. Pilate</hi> himſelfe waſheth his hands from the guilt of that innocent. The Centurion inu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to carnage blud, &amp; butchery, pronounceth, <hi>Aſſuredly this was</hi>
               <note place="margin">54</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:3045:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>a iuſt man.</hi> The verie variable and hundred headed giddie multitude returne knocking their breaſts in remorſe of conſcience, for ſhed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding that pious and pretious guiltleſſe blood of <hi>Ieſus Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For our knowledge then, hence wee inferre, that this praier of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> is the <hi>Foundation, Firma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and Perfection</hi> of the <hi>Church.</hi> The foundation of the <hi>Church,</hi> if wee looke backwards, for it was e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected in <hi>Chriſt</hi> before the world was. This Chapter witneſſeth it, verſe 5. <hi>That Chriſt was with the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 17. 5</note> 
               <hi>before the world was. That hee came out from the father verſ. 8. And that the father loued him before the foundation of the world.</hi> verſe. 24. It is the firmament and aſſurance of the Church, if we reſpect the time preſent, for the calling of God is without recalling: the Golden
<pb facs="tcp:3045:11"/>
Chaine teſtifieth it, <hi>Whome he hath elected before all time, he calleth, iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth, and ſanctifieth in time.</hi> So in<note place="margin">Rom. 8</note> the 15. verſe he praieth not, that the father would take them out of the world, but being in the world, preſerue them from the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uil therof; both, <hi>a malo culpae,</hi> from the euill of ſinne, <hi>a malo penae,</hi> from the euill of puniſhment for ſinne, and alſo, <hi>ab illo malo,</hi> from the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill, and all his deſignements.</p>
            <p>Laſtlie, it is the perfection of the church, if we reſpect the time to come; for hee is the ancient of daies, not to bee antiquated by length of time. He is the perfec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our ſoules and bodies, in the reſurrection; and in a word, our exceeding great reward. So he praieth verſe. 24. <hi>That we may be where he is, that we may behold his glorie which was from euerlaſting.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:3045:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>Of this knowledge of the power of <hi>Chriſts</hi> praier, mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold is the holie, and deuine vſe &amp; practiſe. 1. Of hope which quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth vs. For while we pray heere on earth, wee knowe, and beleeue aſſuredly, that Chriſt praieth for vs, and pleadeth our cauſe as an aduocate in heauen.</p>
            <p>In his humiliation hee praied for vs: in his exaltation then aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuredlie: oh <hi>Angelicall Manna!</hi> 2. Of reuerend boldneſſe, which the ſpirit of God exhorteth. <hi>See<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 4. 14. 15. 16.</note> 
               <hi>then that wee haue a great high Prieſt which is entered into heauen, euen Ieſus the Sonne of God, Let vs hold faſt our profeſsion, for wee haue not an high Prieſt, which cannot be touched with the feeling of our infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, but was in all things tempted in like ſort, yet without ſin. Let vs ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore goe boldly vnto the throane of</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:3045:12"/>
               <hi>grace, that we may receiue mercie, and finde grace to helpe in time of neede.</hi> 3. Of reſolution: if the praier of <hi>Elizeus</hi> was powerfull to reſtore<note place="margin">2. Reg. 4. 36. Act. 20. 12.</note> to life the Sonne of the <hi>Shunamite,</hi> and of <hi>Paul,</hi> to bring againe the <hi>breath of Eutychus;</hi> Why ſhould not wee reſolue to truſt in the Lord, albeit hee kill vs, for he kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth and maketh aliue againe; he laies vs in the duſt, and raiſeth vs vp to euerlaſting and euerliuing glorious felicitie. 4. Of confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, for heere are all the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings of <hi>Garazim</hi> and the dew of <hi>Hermon,</hi> which falleth vppon the hill of <hi>Sion,</hi> (which is Gods <hi>Church</hi>) where the Lord promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth his peace and bleſſing for<note place="margin">Zach. 2. 5.</note> euermore: this is not <hi>murus ahene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us,</hi> but <hi>murus igneus,</hi> not a wall of Braſſe, but of fire; wherein is not onely protection, but terrour and
<pb facs="tcp:3045:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>
vtter deſtruction. Protection to Gods Children: a terrour to their enemies, euen a far off, but if they bee ſo foole hardie, as imagining their skins to be thunder proofe, and approach to hurt his church, they and theirs ſhall bee vtterlie conſumed. 5. Of precedent. wee ought alſo to pray for our ſelues, and for our brethren, for that is a countermure againſt all aſſaults of Sathan, and therfore <hi>Chriſt our Sauiour</hi> ſo aduiſeth vs, <hi>Pray conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk. 18.</note> Laſtly of direction. Chriſt praieth to God the Father imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately, wee therefore in his name onely ought to ſend out our prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, not to Saint or Angell, for that is an iniurie to the whole Trinitie. Firſt, to God the father, who is the obiect of our praiers, ſo himſelfe ſpeaketh: <hi>Call</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſa. 50. 15.</note> 
               <hi>vpon me in the time of trouble, and I</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:3045:13"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:3045:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:3045:14"/>
               <hi>will heare you.</hi> 2. To God the Sonne, for he is the one, and onely mediatour of our praiers. There being but one God, and one me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatour <hi>betweene God and man,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Tim. 2. 5</note> 
               <hi>which is the man Chriſt Ieſus.</hi> 3. To God the holy Ghoſt, for he is the breath of our praiers, <hi>Wee in our ſelues knowing not what to pray for,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 8. 26</note> 
               <hi>nor how to pray as we ought, but the ſpirit it ſelfe maketh request for vs with ſighes vnutterable.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now let vs deſcend from the perſon, which is the Sonne of God, vnto the parties, which are the Sonnes of men. Firſt, as they are deſigned by titles of fauour &amp; honour. Secondly, as they are di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhed by notes of ſeparati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on from the world. <hi>I pray for them which are my Sonnes by adoption,</hi> my Saintes by calling, my Princes and Prieſts by conuerſation; my
<pb facs="tcp:3045:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>
beloued by decree: my baptized by inſtitution: my Illuminates by purpoſe, and mine Aſſociates by promiſe.</p>
            <p>His Sonnes: ſo <hi>Saint Iohn</hi> ſtileth<note place="margin">Iohn. 1. 12.</note> them: <hi>As many as receiued him, to them he gaue prerogatiue to bee the Sonnes of God.</hi> An heauenlie priui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge. The Sons of men, become the ſonnes of God by knowing &amp; acknowledging <hi>Ieſus Chriſt.</hi> The ſame diuine, in words of admired demonſtration, pointeth this out, ſaying, <hi>Behold what loue the father hath giuen to vs, that wee (wretches</hi>) ſhould be called the Sonnes of God. And becauſe the <hi>Euangeliſt thought</hi> it not enough, that wee ſhould be ſo called, he addeth fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: <hi>Deerely beloued,</hi> now are we<note place="margin">1. Io. 3. 1. 2</note> the <hi>Sonnes of God,</hi> but <hi>yet it is not manifeſt what wee ſhall bee.</hi> If then we be ſonnes, ſome vertue toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="tcp:3045:15"/>
with the ſeede is transfu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed. <hi>Bonus ſanguis non mentitur.</hi> Honourable blood cannot coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeit. Whereupon the ſpirit of God warneth vs that we <hi>ſhew our ſelues as Sonnes, not as baſtards,</hi> for<note place="margin">Heb 12. 8</note> whome hee praieth not.</p>
            <p>2 <hi>I pray for them</hi> which are my ſaints by calling, whome I haue purged by my blood, and ſanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by my ſpirit: <hi>The blood of Ieſus</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Ioh. 1. 7</note> 
               <hi>Chriſt purging vs from al our ſinnes.</hi> And <hi>Paul</hi> teſtifieth that <hi>Ieſus Chriſt</hi> was declared mightilie to be the ſonne of God by the ſpirit of ſanc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tification,<note place="margin">Rom. 1</note> not onely in himſelfe, which was powred out on him without meaſure, but alſo vppon euerie one of his in ſome mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure. We ought therefore to bee holy, as our heauenlie father is holie, wee beleeuing alſo a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion of <hi>Saints,</hi> which is ſeene
<pb facs="tcp:3045:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>
by faith, and not by eie.</p>
            <p>3. <hi>I pray for them</hi> which are my Princes, &amp; my Prieſts by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſation. So <hi>Peter</hi> entituleth<note place="margin">1. Pet. 29</note> them: <hi>ye are of the Royall Prieſthood. Royall,</hi> therefore <hi>Princes: Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood,</hi> therefore <hi>Prieſts. Princes</hi> in ſwaying their affections; <hi>Prieſtes</hi> in ſacrificing their <hi>pleaſures,</hi> and in offering their daily ſacrifices to God, for themſelues, &amp; others. In euerie true chriſtian there ſhineth a certaine princely maieſtie, ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned and ſorted with a <hi>Prieſtlie</hi> modeſtie, and humilitie. <hi>Chryſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome</hi> ſaith, they are knowne by their gate, by their looke, by their veſture, by their voice: Their go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing princely; being ſhod with the<note place="margin">Eph. 6. 15.</note> ſhoes of preparation of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell;<note place="margin">Pſal. 131. 1</note> Their lookes <hi>Princely;</hi> being lifted vppe vnto the hils, from whence commeth their helpe:
<pb facs="tcp:3045:16"/>
Their veſture <hi>Prieſtlike,</hi> al glorious<note place="margin">Pſa. 45. 13.</note> within: Their voice <hi>Prieſtlike,</hi> ſoft and milde, as <hi>Iacobs</hi> voice: and theſe are thoſe for whome Chriſt heere praieth.</p>
            <p>4. <hi>I pray alſo for them,</hi> which are my <hi>beloued</hi> by decree: <hi>Beloued</hi> before they were: <hi>Iacob haue I lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued. Beloued</hi> when they were chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren:<note place="margin">Hoſ. 11. 1</note> when <hi>Iſrael</hi> was a childe, <hi>I loued him. Beloued</hi> when they were men: <hi>Zorubbabel,</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Shealtiel,</hi> ſhal be as the ſignet vpon<note place="margin">Hag. vlt.</note> my right hand. <hi>Beloued,</hi> when they are not, <hi>Right deere in the ſight of the Lord is the death of his Saints: yea albeit Beggers, yet beloued, for</hi> an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels attend them, in, &amp; after death<note place="margin">Luc. 16, 22</note> to carrie and conuey them to reſt.</p>
            <p>5 <hi>I pray for them</hi> which are my <hi>Baptized</hi> outwardly by <hi>inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> Inwardly being waſhed from
<pb facs="tcp:3045:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>
their blood with that clean water which <hi>Ezekiel</hi> ſpeaketh of, waſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed<note place="margin">Ez. 16. 9.</note> in mine owne pretious blood, which maketh their garments white, contrarie to al other blood which ſtaineth: for ſo haue the <hi>Saints</hi> waſhed themſelues: and<note place="margin">Apoc. 7. 14</note> their robes waſhed alſo in the lauoure of the new birth, wherby<note place="margin">Tit. 3. 5.</note> they are regenerate to life euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting.</p>
            <p>6 <hi>I pray for them,</hi> which are mine <hi>Illuminats</hi> by purpoſe, which once were darkenes, but now are light in the Lord, for I enlighten euerie one that commeth into the world, but not any that loueth the world. Theſe dwell in <hi>Goſhen</hi> where is alwaies light: and all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſit in darkeneſſe, and in the <hi>Aegiptian</hi> ſhadow of death. Theſe mine <hi>Illuminates</hi> are pure in hart, being purified by faith: they ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore,
<pb facs="tcp:3045:17"/>
ſee God in a three-folde mir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour. 1. They ſee him in his word in the mirrour of <hi>Ieſus Chriſt.</hi> 2. They ſee him in his works, (with<note place="margin">Mat. 5. 8</note> another eye then the worldling doth) in the great diſplaied book of heauen and earth. 3. And laſtlie, heereafter ſhall ſee him face to face in heauen with Ieſus Chriſt, and the holie Angels.</p>
            <p>7 <hi>I pray for them</hi> which are mine <hi>Aſſociates</hi> by promiſe, partaking of mine owne name, beeing Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians.<note place="margin">Act, 11. 26</note> At <hi>Antioch</hi> they were firſt called Chriſtians; now heere, and in all the Chriſtian world. Saint <hi>Ambroſe</hi> his iudgement of theſe Aſſociates was ſo deere, that hee reades that place, Gal. 5, 24. <hi>Qui ſunt Chriſti,</hi> in the nominatiue plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, not as it is vulgarly taken in the genitiue ſingular: As if hee ſhould obſerue, that ſo manie
<pb facs="tcp:3045:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Chriſtians, are ſo many <hi>Chriſts,</hi> by reaſon of this holy and heauenlie <hi>vnion</hi> and <hi>Aſſociation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The vſe then (<hi>bleſſed Brethren</hi>) is, that wee ſeeke, and endeuour by all might and meanes to cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpond theſe gratious, glorious, and ennobled titles. Otherwiſe, what are wee with theſe pretious titles, but like the boxes and pots of the Apothecarie, which out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly haue ſome goodlie exo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tique inſcription, when within, is ſome vnwholeſome, vnſauory drug: or like the <hi>Mahumetanes</hi> which at this day call themſelues <hi>Saraſins,</hi> as if they came of <hi>Sara</hi> the free woman, when as indeede<note place="margin">Zozom. Eccleſ. Hiſt. 6. 38.</note> they are <hi>Hagarines</hi> of <hi>Hagar,</hi> and <hi>Iſmael</hi> (as <hi>Zozomen</hi> a thouſand yeares agoe obſerued:) which ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth euen yet by their wicked and diſſolute condition at this
<pb facs="tcp:3045:18"/>
day. Or like thoſe that row in a bote, ſit with their faces toward you, but row the bote backward: ſo ſome make ſemblance of going on in a direct courſe, and chriſtian carriage, when their actions and proceedings are directlie contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riant.</p>
            <p>With ſuch I may expoſtulate and ſay, what haſt thou to doe with the name of <hi>Sonne,</hi> when like a baſtard thy condition is to ſhame thy father, and diſhonor thy mother? Thou cauſeſt God, whome thou boaſteſt to bee thy father, to bee contemned, and the <hi>Church</hi> thy mother to be deſpiſed. What haſt thou to doe with the name of <hi>Saint,</hi> when as thou art a Slaue to ſinne, and a bond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlaue to ſathan? what haſt thou to doe with the title of <hi>Prince,</hi> or <hi>Prieſt,</hi> when as thou canſt finde in
<pb facs="tcp:3045:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>
thine heart, nay boaſt of it, that thou art an age<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t againſt Prince, &amp; Prieſt in the vileſt actions. Or why boaſteſt thou of the honour of <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued,</hi> when as thou art hatefull to God &amp; good men? or of thy <hi>Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm,</hi> ſeeing thou art of that foliſh<note place="margin">Pro. 30. 12</note> &amp; fond generation, that are pure in their own conceit, and art not clenſed &amp; baptized from their vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleannes? Or of thine <hi>Illumination,</hi> when as thou gropeſt at mid-day, as did the ancient heretikes, the <hi>Gnoſtikes,</hi> who imagined that they had an impropriatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Gods ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, that none had true knowledge but they, and as the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> &amp; <hi>Ieſuits</hi> with the late fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded order of the confou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded <hi>congregatio Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torij,</hi> who at this day in this glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous light of the Goſpell of Chriſt, grope in <hi>Cymmerian</hi> dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and gape after vnwrit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten
<pb facs="tcp:3045:19"/>
reuelations. Laſtlie, what haue you to doe with the name of <hi>chriſtian</hi> when as ye are indeed <hi>Cretians,</hi> of whome that of<note place="margin">Tit. 1. 2.</note> 
               <hi>Epimenides</hi> is fully verified: <hi>The Cretians are alwaies liars, euil beaſts, ſlow bellies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But I am perſwaded better things of you, my brethren. At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend you therefore as Sonnes: and if ought afflict you, call and crie vnto your heauenlie father, who doth tender you as Sonnes, and as Saints: reſolue that here we haue no abiding Citie, but we ſeek one to come: let your conuerſation bee therefore as they that looke for ſo glorious an eſtate in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen. And as <hi>Princes and Priests,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 119. 164. Dan. 6. 10.</note> 
               <hi>with Dauid ſeauen times a day: and with Dauid three times a day Pray, &amp; praiſe the Lord.</hi> You that are the beloued of the lord: let neither life
<pb facs="tcp:3045:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>
nor death ſeparate you from that vnſpeakeable loue: nor the power of darkeneſſe, nor the gates of hell, for none of all theſe preuaile againſt the beloued of the Lord. And, as truely <hi>Baptized children,</hi> and waſhed in the righteouſnes of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> ſay with the ſpouſe in the<note place="margin">Can. 5. 7</note> 
               <hi>Canticles, I haue waſhed my feete, how ſhould I defile them? I will by</hi> no meanes wallowe againe in the mire. You are <hi>illuminated</hi> of the Lord by the pretious eye ſalue of his truth, being blind and darkned before through the ignorance that was in you. Giue glorie ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore vnto the Lord, as the blind in the Goſpel, who were reſtored to their ſight. And laſtly, as true <hi>chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians aſſociated to Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> bee zealous in the Lords ſeruice, as were the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> in the primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue church, who being in perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution,
<pb facs="tcp:3045:20"/>
and dailie ſubiect to blou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die butcherie, yet praied and prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the Lord in the dens &amp; caues of the earth, as <hi>Plinius Secundus</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen their aduerſarie in the time of <hi>Traianus</hi> the emperour teſtifieth of them. But you, bleſſed brethren haue your oratories open, your pulpits frequented, with free and gratious paſſage; let not the fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uencie of theſe diſtreſſed Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians riſe vp againſt you in the day of iudgement, who are thus bleſſed euerie way, and beloued euerie day of the Lord of heauen and of earth, that he may pray for you, and ſo you may be euermore bleſſed in the ſurpaſſing fauour of <hi>Ieſus Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Remember alſo that as you are thus deſigned, by titles of fauour and honour, that you alſo ſhew your ſelues both to your owne
<pb facs="tcp:3045:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>
ſoules, &amp; to others, as the people that are diſtinguiſhed, and ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from the men of this world. For our Sauiour heere in this place, ſaith, <hi>I pray not for the world, but for them:</hi> which diſcretiue <hi>But,</hi> diſtinguiſheth, &amp; demonſtrateth that you are not of the world, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit you are in the world.</p>
            <p>That you are not of the world, three infallible notes of ſeparati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on muſt declare. And here let no man traduce this word <hi>Separation,</hi> for I vnderſtand not thereby anie <hi>Anabaptiſticall</hi> or <hi>Browniſh ſeperati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> but the ſame that <hi>Paul</hi> meneth, though in a diuers matter. For as he ſpeaketh of <hi>Separation,</hi> or ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting apart of Preachers, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>:<note place="margin">Ro. 11. 19</note> ſo I ſay, heere is a <hi>Seperation</hi> of true Chriſtians, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>The notes of this diuine <hi>Sepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:3045:21"/>
are three. 1. A <hi>Catholike</hi> faith toward God. 2. <hi>Integritie</hi> of life and conuerſation in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues. 3. <hi>Euangelicall</hi> charitie toward others.</p>
            <p>By a <hi>Catholik</hi> Faith, I vnderſtand, not a <hi>Romiſh,</hi> rotten, ragged, nouel profeſſion: nor as theſe rare <hi>illumi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated Ieſuits</hi> vnderſtand <hi>Catholike,</hi> who among manie, and manifold other their trauerſing the point how to vnderſtand <hi>Catholik</hi> at laſt conclude verie holie (God wot) that none are <hi>Catholik</hi> profeſſors, and of that faith, but ſuch as are vnder the <hi>Catholike Biſhop,</hi> the <hi>Pope</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> in the gouernment and tie of their ſoules and conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, and vnder the Catholike King of Spaine, in the regiment<note place="margin">Sparing Diſcouery of Eng. Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuits.</note> of their bodies &amp; goods. And this deuice was then hatched when they intended to haue raiſed that
<pb facs="tcp:3045:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>Phillip</hi> of <hi>Spaine</hi> to haue beene the <hi>weſtern Monarch</hi> of this part of the world. Thus doe theſe Ieſuiticall impoſtours abuſe and abaſe theſe ſacred myſteries of Faith, and the ſeruice of God, to damnable and deteſtable policie. But wee (belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued of the Lord) vnderſtand a <hi>ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike</hi> faith, either as the current of the fathers, that is, the ortho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doxe Faith, or as <hi>Vincentius Lyri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nenſis</hi>
               <note place="margin">Vincent. Contr. Hor. Ca. 3.</note> thirteene hundred yeares a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goe interpreteth Catholike, to wit, That which hath beene re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued and beleeued euerie where in the chriſtian world, in al places, at all times, and of all true confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors.<note place="margin">Heb. 12</note> And without this faith, wee conclude with the <hi>Apoſtle, That it is impoſsible to pleaſe God.</hi> The reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence whereof is in the heart: <hi>for with the heart we beleeue to righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ro. 10. 10</note> So <hi>Philip</hi> the Euangeliſt teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
<pb facs="tcp:3045:22"/>
the <hi>Eunuch. If thou beleeue with</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 8. 37.</note> 
               <hi>all thine heart thou maiſt bee bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The effects of this Catholike faith, are foure, manifeſted in the word: 1. A reſolued truſt in God. 2. A reuerend boldneſſe toward him. 3. An euidence of things not ſeene. 4. A plenarie perſwaſion and full ſetling of the heart. The two firſt are reuealed in one verſ: <hi>Seeing then that we haue ſuch truſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Cor. 3. 12</note> ſaith <hi>Paul, we vſe great boldneſſe of ſpeech.</hi> The fourth is verified, as of <hi>Abrahams</hi> faith, which is a perfect paterne, ſo of all the faithfull, <hi>That hee was fully perſwaded, that he</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 4. 24</note> 
               <hi>which had promiſed, was able to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme it, and therefore it was imputed to him for righteouſnes.</hi> The third is poſitiuely ſet downe of the ſpirit of God: <hi>That faith is the ground of</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 11. 1</note> 
               <hi>things hoped for, and the euidence of</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:3045:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>things not euident.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus may we diſcerne a <hi>Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like</hi> Faith by the ſtile, and by the effects. Furthermore, we may deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crie it by looking vpon thoſe halfe faced chriſtians, which haue not this true character &amp; ſtamp vpon them. As firſt, thoſe are not of this <hi>Catholique Faith,</hi> who ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue part of the commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, &amp; reiect the other part, as an <hi>Hypocriticall Faith</hi> doth. For the hypocrites are preciſe in the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruance of the firſt table, but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſe in the cautions of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond table. And this is Sans que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, an infallible note of a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe Hypocrite, if you mark it. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, thoſe that willingly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue part of the Articles of our creed, and neglect the other part, are not of this <hi>Catholike faith.</hi> For whereas the whole ſumme of our
<pb facs="tcp:3045:23"/>
Faith is referred to thoſe three heads. 1. <hi>Ad eſſe Matura. 2. Ad eſſe Gratiae. 3. Ad eſse Gloriae.</hi> The chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> partee perpale, as the heralds ſpeak, condiſcendeth to the cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit that God made the world, which is the firſt generall head, and willingly heareth of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed glory in the world to come but when he is brought to the hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliation, death, and reſurrection of Chriſt, and is bound hereby to humble, mortifie, and conforme himſelfe according to the Image of the ſonne of God, there hee fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth, and leaueth off his proceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and going on in this <hi>Catholike Faith.</hi> Thirdly, thoſe are not of this <hi>Catholike</hi> Faith, who thinke they may ſerue Idols outwardly: ſo they keepe their Faith to God inwardly, like vnto <hi>Peter</hi> in the Pallace of the High prieſt, and the
<pb facs="tcp:3045:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>
ancient <hi>Heretiques</hi> the <hi>Helchiſitae</hi> who imagined they might doe as others doe in the outward wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, ſo that they kept their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences and hearts to God: as though God were not the <hi>Creator</hi> of their bodies, as well as of their ſoules; &amp; required not the whole man to ſerue him. Fourthly, they are not of this catholik faith, who ſerue God onely outwardly, as do all worldly chriſtians. Fiftly, they are not of this <hi>Catholik</hi> faith, who ſerue God onelie in their time of proſperitie; for both theſe ſorts are condemned and reiected by our <hi>Sauiour</hi> in the parable of the ſeed. Laſtly, they are not of this<note place="margin">Luke. 8.</note> 
               <hi>Catholike Fath,</hi> who ſerue him in certaine places, as in the court, and not in the countrie, in the countrie, and not in the court. Theſe are ſuch as Chriſt praieth
<pb facs="tcp:3045:24"/>
not for, but are excluded from the holy Communion of his bleſſed interceſſion. <hi>Dauids</hi> ſpirit &amp; faith was other wiſe: for he ſaith, I will<note place="margin">Pſal. 119</note> 
               <hi>ſpeake of thy teſtmonies before kings, and will not bee aſhamed.</hi> What an hideous ſhame was this, euen in the time of Chriſts Incarnation, <hi>That among the cheefe Rulers many beleeued in him; but becauſe of the Phariſees they did not confeſſe him, leſt they ſhould bee caſt out of the Synagogue:</hi> but the reaſon enſueth;<note place="margin">Ioh. 12</note> 
               <hi>They loued the praiſe of men, more then the praiſe of GOD.</hi> O foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh and faithleſſe people, be ye Gouernors, Rulers, Iudges, or Inferiors, heare your doome; with <hi>what meaſure yee mete with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, ſhall bee meaſured to you againe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> chriſt auoucheth it, <hi>whoſoeuer,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>ſhall confeſſe mee before men,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 10, 32 33.</note> 
               <hi>him will I confeſſe alſo before my</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:3045:24" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>Father which is in heauen. But whoſoeuer ſhall denie mee before men, him will I alſo denie before my Father which is in heauen.</hi> And<note place="margin">Luk, 9, 26</note> againe, <hi>whoſoeuer ſhall bee aſhamed of mee, and of my words, of him ſhall the Sonne of man bee aſhamed, when hee ſhall come in his glorie, and in the glorie of the father, and of the holy angels.</hi> Thus much of the firſt note of true chriſtianity; which is a <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholik</hi> faith toward God.</p>
            <p>The ſecond is Sinceritie, and Newnes of life and conuerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in our ſelues. And herein ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth the wonderful power &amp; maieſtie of our God, in that wee haue ſtrength, through him, to ſanctifie in ſome meaſure our wre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tched and accurſed nature. For as the true Chriſtian, for whom Chriſt here prayeth, liueth two liues, a natural life, &amp; a ſupernatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral,
<pb facs="tcp:3045:25"/>
ſo hath god giuen him two forms whereby thoſe liues are ſuſtained. For firſt, as by the ſoule, which is the naturall forme, we liue a natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall life, in all our powers and ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces: ſo of grace which is the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pernatural, forme proceed all the vertues, and gifts of Gods ſpirit, whereby wee liue a ſupernaturall life. This was <hi>Pauls</hi> life after he was conuerted, when as he teſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, <hi>That he liued not, but Chriſt li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued in him.</hi> In like manner the ſpouſe alſo in the Canticles expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtulateth with temptations: <hi>I haue put off my coate, how ſhould I put it on againe?</hi> that is, ſhee had caſt away the works of darknes; how ſhould ſhe take them againe? <hi>I haue waſhed</hi>
               <note place="margin">Can. 5. 3.</note> 
               <hi>my feete, how ſhould I defile them?</hi> that is, I am become cleane in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing purified by faith in the blood of Chriſt, and haue done away all
<pb facs="tcp:3045:25" rendition="simple:additions"/>
my former filthes, how can I now, that reioyce that I am thus de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered, return into that bondage and ſlauerie againe?</p>
            <p>The vſe of this then is (becauſe I haſten) that we deceiue not our ſelues: for what ſemblance ſoeuer wee make outwardly of chriſtian profeſſion, yet if we doe not ſanc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie our ſelues in ſome meaſure, there is no truth in vs; and we doe but coſen our owne conſciences, and become traitors to our owne ſoules. For this is poſitiue; That<note place="margin">Pſal. 19. 1. Ioh. 3. 3.</note> 
               <hi>the feare of the Lord is cleane.</hi> And, <hi>he that hath a hope of heauen, doth purge himſelf.</hi> If I might craue of you (bleſſed people) to remember but this paralel of ſcripture, it ſhal be ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t for me to bleſſe (al the daies of my life) this my poore la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boure and trauel. And ſo I wil deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cend vnto my third note of <hi>Sepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:3045:26"/>
whereby thoſe, that here Chriſt prayeth for, are diſtingui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed from the world: to wit, <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uangelical Charitie,</hi> which is indeed the Cogniſance of a true <hi>Catholike</hi> Chriſtian.</p>
            <p>So our Sauiour teſtifieth, ſaying, <hi>By this ſhall all men know you to be my</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 13. 35</note> 
               <hi>diſciples, if ye loue one another:</hi> which Loue is not in the mouth &amp; tong onely, but in <hi>truth and veritie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That this is the true outward di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction<note place="margin">1 Ioh. 13. 3.</note> of a true <hi>Catholike Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an,</hi> it appeareth to all of vs heere preſent. For it is common to all profeſſors, to be receiued into the Church by <hi>Baptiſme: to enter into the aſſemblies to praier and preaching: to bold vp their handes, and cast vp their eies to heauen: to crie, Lord haue mercie vppon vs: and in concluſion to ſay, Amen.</hi> Yet many of theſe are counterſet Chriſtians, fained, and
<pb facs="tcp:3045:26" rendition="simple:additions"/>
falſe diſſemblers: but Charitie, and Loue <hi>Euangelicall</hi> notifieth vnto vs the faithfull profeſſor, from the fained and falſe diſſembler.</p>
            <p>There are foure fountaines from whence Loue ſpringeth: the. 1. of <hi>Nature,</hi> and that euen is alſo the inſtinct of brute beaſtes. The. 2. of <hi>Blood,</hi> and that is of Naturall men, as they are meerely naturall. The 3. of <hi>Reaſon;</hi> and that is the league and amitie of Philoſophers, who take <hi>Reaſon</hi> to bee their Pilot; and Loue no farther than they haue Reaſon. The. 4. of <hi>Grace;</hi> and that is properly of true Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, and that I call <hi>Euangelicall Charitie.</hi> The properties whereof are: 1. To ſympathize with others in their diſtreſſe: <hi>Beare one anothers burthen.</hi> 2. To pray for one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: <hi>The Chriſtian Sacrifice.</hi> 3. To ſuffer, beare and forbeare, euen
<pb facs="tcp:3045:27"/>
with the conditions of them that hate vs, yea, and doe good vnto them, and this is indeed the exal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of Chriſtian charity: which <hi>Euangelicall</hi> and gratious charitie is twofold, either <hi>in affectu,</hi> or <hi>in effectu.</hi> In affection onely the poore ſhew their loue, from whom the Lord accepts the will, euen as the deed: for he requireth not that of them, which he giueth not vnto them: but in the rich this charitie muſt bee effectuall in diſtributing, and deſperſing the bleſſings and benefits of the Lord to his poore people.</p>
            <p>Witneſſe therfore (bleſſed audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torie in the Lord <hi>Ieſus</hi>) this day; that it is a ſlander and calumnia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the <hi>Papiſt,</hi> who ſaith, that we teach you negatiue doctrines onely, and not affirmatiue. For wee eft-ſoones proclaime vnto
<pb facs="tcp:3045:27" rendition="simple:additions"/>
you from this place, and all other the like in this kingdome, that your <hi>Catholike</hi> Faith is a dead and deſperate follie if it worke not by loue, for loue is the euidence to your ſelues, and to the world of your Faith to God. But alas, with horror and amazement be it ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, how many are there that make profeſſion of this <hi>Catholike</hi> faith, and <hi>Euangelicall charitie,</hi> and yet are degenerated beneath brute beaſts in the courſe of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and bloud, as becomming a cruell <hi>Oedipus</hi> to their father, and a curſed <hi>Nero</hi> vnto their mother! Yea, euen in their reaſon become more vnthankfull then <hi>Iudas,</hi> and that to thoſe, to whom they owe<note place="margin">Phil. v. 19.</note> in all right and reaſon, euen their owne ſoules: yet are they inhu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane as the Dog, and cruel as the <hi>Lioneſſe,</hi> whereas <hi>Euangelicall chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:3045:28"/>
as hath beene ſaid, is extended euen vnto our enemies, after the example of our God, who ſhineth with his ſun vpon the good and bad, and of <hi>Chriſt Ieſus</hi> our Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, and of the <hi>Protomartyr</hi> Saint <hi>Stephen,</hi> our fellow ſouldier, who praied for their tyrannous perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutors; but much more then to our brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, to the diſtreſſed, nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, and afflicted members of our Lord Chriſt. Let it bee then a brand of impietie againſt that ſoule in the day of account, who heareth this, and regardeth it not, ſeeing it is the peremptorie and poſitiue aſſertion of the Sonne of God, <hi>That by this Euangelical cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 3. 35</note> 
               <hi>all men ſhall know who are his.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thus much for the perſon, praier and parties both deſigned and diſtinguiſhed. Now let vs proceed to the reaſons, why hee
<pb facs="tcp:3045:28" rendition="simple:additions"/>
praieth for them. 1. <hi>Donatiue, which thou haſt giuen me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This giuing of vs to God the father, is nothing elſe but a mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtation of the determinate pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe of God in <hi>Ieſus Chriſt:</hi> for as God the father hath predeſtina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vs to the end, which is his glory, euerlaſting life: ſo alſo hath he predeſtinate vs to the meanes, to bring vs therunto, &amp; they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be eluded. The father hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen vs to his Sonne, to ſerue him in foure eſpeciall ſuites and ſeruices: 1. in deuoted religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, euen as the ſonne himſelfe doth, who ſaith heere in this chapter, verſe 4. <hi>I glorifie the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> ſo muſt we that bee Chriſts ſeruants; <hi>Let our light ſo ſhine before</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat 5. 16.</note> 
               <hi>men, that they ſeeing our good works may glorifie our Father which is in heauen.</hi> 2. In the zeale of ſoules.
<pb facs="tcp:3045:29"/>
               <hi>For the zeale of the Lord muſt euen</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 69. 9</note> 
               <hi>eate vs vp. Monica</hi> the mother of <hi>Auguſtine</hi> is a rare Preſident heerein. What prayers, ſighes, and groanes did that godly mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther<note place="margin">Aug. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſ.</note> make for her ſonne <hi>Auguſtine</hi> yet being a <hi>Maniche,</hi> that hee might become an <hi>Orthodox?</hi> Such was the zeale of that pious mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for the ſoule of her deere Sonne. <hi>Paul</hi> alſo became all vnto all, that hee might winne the more: who was weake, and he was not weake? Thirdly in humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie:<note place="margin">Mich. 6. 8.</note> for the Prophet <hi>Micheas</hi> expoſtulating this point, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withall hee ſhould come before the Lord, in the end concludeth, that a man muſt humble himſelfe to walke with his God, ſhewing that there is no other meanes whereby man may tread the ſteps of the holy ſeruice of God, but by
<pb facs="tcp:3045:29" rendition="simple:additions"/>
an humble deiectment of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to the maieſty of God. So al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo our Sauiour himſelfe teacheth vs when he ſaith, <hi>Learn of me, for I</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 11, 29</note> 
               <hi>am meeke and lowly in heart, and yee ſhall finde reſt vnto your ſoules.</hi> Laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, in bearing the Croſſe, not a woodden Croſſe, or a golden cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifixe, or an <hi>Agnus Dei,</hi> or any ſuch Romiſh rudiment, or guileful merchandize, but a conſtant pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe of holie life, which is indeed the bearing of the Croſſe: <hi>for</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Tim. 3. 12.</note> 
               <hi>whoſo will liue godlie in Chriſt Ieſus, ſhall ſuffer perſecution,</hi> and haue croſſe as much as his backe will beare, which croſſe wee muſt take vp, not auoide or ſhun, and follow <hi>Chriſt Ieſus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond reaſon is taken from God the fathers poſſeſſion of vs, in theſe words (<hi>for they are thine.</hi>) We are God the fathers,
<pb facs="tcp:3045:30"/>
whether wee looke backwards or forwards; backwards both by<note place="margin">Ioh 15.</note> 
               <hi>Election,</hi> and alſo by <hi>Creation.</hi> By <hi>Election:</hi> for ſo it is ſaid, <hi>You haue</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eph. 1. 4.</note> 
               <hi>not choſen mee, but I haue choſen you,</hi> and that <hi>before the world was.</hi> By <hi>Creation:</hi> ſo ſaith the <hi>Pſalmiſt, Thy hands haue made mee, and faſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned me,</hi> and in ſuch an admirable<note place="margin">Pſa. 119. 73</note> manner, as hee hath denied to all others his creatures, for hee hath made vs after his owne Image. If we looke forward, wee are his by <hi>Sanctification and Glorification.</hi> By <hi>Sanctification:</hi> for ſo he ſaith to the church of <hi>Laodicea<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Behold I ſtand at the doore and knocke: If any man heare my voice, and open the doore, I</hi>
               <note place="margin">Apoc. 3. 2<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>wil come in vnto him, and banquet with him, and he with me.</hi> What is this knocking, but his calling vnto vs by his word, workes and bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits? what is this doore, but the
<pb facs="tcp:3045:30" rendition="simple:additions"/>
cloſet of our hearts? what is this hearing, but our obeying? what is this opening, but the readineſſe of our ſoules? <hi>My heart is ready,</hi> ſaith <hi>Dauid.</hi> This comming into vs? but his being in vs by his holie ſpirit, whereby he taketh liuery and ſei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of vs? What this banquetting, he with vs, and we with him, but the continuall feaſt of a good and a godlie conſcience? And by <hi>Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rification</hi> wee are his: for his wee were, we are, and ſhall be for euer and euer. <hi>All the promiſes in Chriſt</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Cor. 1. 20</note> 
               <hi>being Yea, and Amen.</hi> Attend then the ſumme of both the reaſons. We are the gifts of GOD to his ſonne, therefore his freely, <hi>ſupremo iure</hi> in the higheſt right. <hi>Paul</hi> precheth it in one verſe by a moſt heauenlie and diuine ſpeech of degrees, where hee ſaith, <hi>All things are ours,</hi> and prooueth it by enu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meration
<pb facs="tcp:3045:31"/>
of particulars in an ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable gradation: <hi>Whether it bee</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Co. 3. 21. 22. 23.</note> 
               <hi>Paul, or Apollos, or Cephas, or the world, or life, or death, whether they be things preſent or things to come, euen all are yours, and you Chriſts, &amp; Chriſt Gods.</hi> Oh holie honour! oh diuine conſolation! Behold, I ſay, and looke with your eies of faith vnto this angelicall dignitie, and bee rauiſhed in the ſpirit with this ſurpaſſing and exceeding fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour of God, in giuing vs (wretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es) vnto his Sonne, as if his Sonne were not compleat without vs: as if there were no better things to beſtow in the whole frame of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture vpon his beloued, then vs miſerable &amp; duſt-creeping crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. And as though hee had for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>got all other creatures of heauen and of earth, and ſet his eie of fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour and affection vpon vs one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly:
<pb facs="tcp:3045:31" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Man and Angels fall; the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels<note place="margin">Iud. ver. 6.</note> are reſerued in chaines of darkeneſſe, vnto the great day of the Lord. But for man he ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned a <hi>Sauiour,</hi> remembred wherof he was made, &amp; according to his tender compaſſion, &amp; multitudes of his mercies ſaued him, and gaue him to his Sonne, that through him hee might haue fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour toward man, delight in him, and bee one with him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>O ye bleſſed of the Lord,</hi> note then in the firſt reaſon, that God giueth to his Sonne no prophane <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſt,</hi> curſed <hi>Achriſt,</hi> or irreligious wanton, or that perſon who ſhall ſay in his heart, <hi>religentem eſſe opor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tet, religioſum nefas;</hi> as if it were a <hi>piaculum</hi> to be deuoutly religious. 2. Nor any remiſſe and careleſſe companion, who hath as much care of his brothers ſoule, as of
<pb facs="tcp:3045:32"/>
his owne, and ſaith in <hi>Cains</hi> curſed voice, <hi>Am I my Brothers keeper?</hi> no indeed, how can he bee his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers keeper, when he hath no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of his owne keeping? who can ſuffer Chriſt to bee crucified daily before his eies, and not bee mooued therewith? 3. Nor any imperious ruffian, for God reſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the proud. 4. Nor any ſuch as flie the Croſſe, who would with <hi>Balaam</hi> die the death of the godly, but will not liue their life: would haue Angels in their end conuey them into <hi>Abrahams</hi> bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, but all their life care not for God, nor Angell, Saint nor Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell.</p>
            <p>And further, learne out of the ſecond reaſon: 1. Of your <hi>Electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on:</hi> That hee hath elected you in Chriſt, which excludeth all merit.<note place="margin">Epheſ. 1.</note> 2. That hee hath choſen you in
<pb facs="tcp:3045:32" rendition="simple:additions"/>
himſelfe, therefore hee found no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in vs worthy of election or remembrance. 2. Of your <hi>Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion:</hi> that wee wholly giue ouer our ſelues vnto him, who hath made vs that we may bee guided and ruled by his holy and heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie directions. 3. Of our <hi>Sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication:</hi> that wee quench not the<note place="margin">1. The. 5. 19</note> ſpirit of Gods good motions that he kindleth in vs, nor deſpiſe that bleſſed grace whereby we are ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to <hi>Saluation.</hi> 4. Of our <hi>Glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication,</hi> that we ſet our affections <hi>on heauen and heauenly things, &amp; not</hi>
               <note place="margin">Col. 3. 2.</note> 
               <hi>on earth and earthly things,</hi> but ſeek thoſe things which are aboue, <hi>where Chriſt ſitteth at the right hand of God.</hi> Thus by degrees haue we aſcended <hi>Iacobs</hi> ladder, &amp; lifted vp our thoughts vnto the higheſt heauens, euen to our holy and heauenly Mediator Chriſt Ieſus.
<pb facs="tcp:3045:33"/>
And now I muſt end this Song of <hi>Sion,</hi> the diuine ſolace of the religious ſoule; and deſcend from heauen to earth, euen vnto the ſecond generall part, the woe of the worldlings, in theſe words, <hi>I pray not for the world.</hi> Wherin note three obſeruances. 1. The perſon <hi>I.</hi> 2. The exception, <hi>I pray not.</hi> 3. The deſignation, <hi>for the world.</hi> Firſt of the perſon. As in the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer part wee conſidered him in his name and nature, ſo now let vs looke vpon him in his offices, to cleere the obiections of Cauil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, namely, how it is conſonant to his diuine offices of <hi>King, Prieſt</hi> and <hi>Prophet,</hi> that hee ſhould not pray for the world.</p>
            <p>Firſt then of his kingly office: How ſorteth it therewith, that he being a <hi>King,</hi> ſhould come into the world, and not pray for it?
<pb facs="tcp:3045:33" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Indeede ſome erroneous <hi>Iewes</hi> dreamed that the kingdome of the <hi>Meſsias</hi> ſhould bee a tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall eſtate. And there were a rout of heretikes called <hi>Herodians,</hi> flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terers in <hi>Herods</hi> Court, who pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended <hi>Herod</hi> to bee the true and vndoubted <hi>Meſsias.</hi> Yea the very Diſciples of Chriſt alſo were in a quandarie of this ſurmiſe, when they asked Chriſt whether now <hi>he would reſtore the Kingdome to Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 1. 6</note> But Chriſt himſelfe anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth this obiection very plainely, where he ſaith, That <hi>his Kingdome is not of this world.</hi> Therefore it is conſonant, that he as a King prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not for the world.</p>
            <p>As touching his Prieſthood, many and manifold are the obie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions; but they may be reduced briefly to theſe foure heads: The firſt drawen from the power of
<pb facs="tcp:3045:34"/>
his paſſion. The ſecond from the equitie of his will. The third from his owne practiſe. And the fourth from Apoſtolicall exhortation. 1. From the power of his paſſion is obiected that of Saint <hi>Iohn: He</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Ioh. 2. 2.</note> 
               <hi>is the reconciliation for our ſins, and not for ours only, but for the ſinnes of the whole world.</hi> Why therefore doth hee not pray for the world, ſeeing hee is the propitiation for the ſinnes of the whole world? The ſame <hi>Euangelist</hi> elſwhere an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwereth it: <hi>He came indeed vnto his</hi>
               <note place="margin">Io. 1. 11. 12<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> 
               <hi>owne, but his owne receiued him not. But to as many as receiued him, to them he gaue this prerogatiue, to bee the ſonnes of God.</hi> Their deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and deſertion therefore is of themſelues, becauſe they do not receiue him. The ſecond obie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction drawen from the equitie of his will, is that of <hi>S. Peter,</hi> where<note place="margin">2. Pet. 3.</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:3045:34" rendition="simple:additions"/>
it is ſaid that he <hi>would that all men</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Pet. 3.</note> 
               <hi>ſhould bee ſaued.</hi> How then can that bee, ſeeing heere hee praieth not for all men? The anſwer here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto is, that his will is two-fold: to wit, <hi>voluntas Signi,</hi> and <hi>voluntas Beneplaciti.</hi> His reuealed will, and his concealed will. He praieth, ſaith Saint <hi>Auguſtine:</hi> thats his<note place="margin">Aug. in Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>han.</note> mercie. <hi>For he hath mercie on whom hee wil haue mercy.</hi> He praieth not: thats his iuſtice. <hi>For there are veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 9.</note> 
               <hi>of wrath prepared for deſtruction.</hi> The third obiection is taken from his owne practiſe, for hee praied for his enemies, <hi>father forgiue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> The anſwer: <hi>Christ</hi> was then the Lambe of God, and in his dee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſt humiliation, wherein hee ſhewed all tokens of meekeneſſe and mercie, but heere in the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhment of the ſheep from the Goates, he is the Lion, of the
<pb facs="tcp:3045:35"/>
royall blood of <hi>Iuda,</hi> that rendeth in peeces his aduerſaries, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uideth the ſpoile. The fourth ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iection from <hi>Apoſtolicall</hi> exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, is, that of Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> who ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horteth,<note place="margin">1. Tim. 2. 1</note> 
               <hi>That praiers and ſupplica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions bee made for all men.</hi> The an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer: This word <hi>All</hi> is not to be vnderſtood <hi>de ſingulis generum,</hi> but <hi>de generibus ſingulorum:</hi> as that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo in our <hi>Liturgy, That it may pleaſe thee to haue mercie vpon all men:</hi> which ſome haue made an nicetie of, is not vnderſtood <hi>collectiuè,</hi> but <hi>diſtributiuè,</hi> as Maſter <hi>Perkins</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenteth.</p>
            <p>But that of <hi>Cyrill</hi> meeteth al ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iections, and deſcendeth to the third office of Chriſt, as hee is a Prophet. For that ancient Father ſaith, Chriſt ſpeaketh heere <hi>ſpiritu prophetic<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>;</hi> for obſerue the maner: In his paſſion hee praieth for his
<pb facs="tcp:3045:35" rendition="simple:additions"/>
aduerſaries; not mentioning his Diſciples: heere hee praieth for his Diſciples, and excludeth his enemies. Neither is this diſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant from <hi>Dauid</hi> his tune, when he ſaid, <hi>Let their Table bee made a</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 6 9.</note> 
               <hi>ſnare, bow downe their backs, and let that which was for their wealth bee vnto them an occaſion of falling,</hi> and the like: for this is no imprecation, but a prophecie, that ſo it ſhal be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fall the accurſed, the Lords ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> is of the ſame iudgement. Chriſt might (ſaith <hi>Auguſtine</hi>) haue praied in ſilence vnto his heauenlie father, but hee would not: Firſt, becauſe he might be an example vnto his Diſciples that they might alſo pray. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condlie, that hee might make knowne vnto them the myſteries of the kingdome of heauen, to whom they belonged, whereof
<pb facs="tcp:3045:36"/>
this was not the leaſt; to wit: That the vngodly had no portion with them of the praier of their Lord and Sauiour. But let vs heare Chriſt himſelfe: Firſt excluding the reprobates in generall in this verſe, <hi>I pray not for the world:</hi> and ſecondly in particular, excepting <hi>Iudas,</hi> as you ſee, verſe 12. Where you may obſerue that he praieth not for his confuſedly, but parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly: <hi>for the Lord knoweth who are his.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now then ye ſee that as he is a king, he anſwereth, <hi>My kingdome is not of this world.</hi> As he is a Prieſt, all receiue him not, albeit he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer &amp; offer himſelfe vnto all, and as a Prophet he foretelleth what ſhall bee the portion of the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked to drinke. But if any ſhall bee yet curious, and obiect that the perſon of the Sonne of God, ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered
<pb facs="tcp:3045:36" rendition="simple:additions"/>
which is ſufficient. I anſwer that the Paſcall Lambe profited the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> onely, and not the <hi>Aegyptians.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The vſe of all this is, Firſt, that the promiſes of God doe onelie concerne the faithfull. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let men remember that of <hi>Saint Auguſtine: Sperando &amp; deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perando miſerè pereunt homines,</hi> by hoping wickedly, and wantonlie all their life in the mercy of God, &amp; deſparing worſe in their death, by forſaking the liuing Lord, men miſerably periſh. The ſecond vſe is, that albeit <hi>Paul</hi> preach, yet <hi>Chriſt is indeed to ſome the righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of God,</hi> but to others the <hi>Rock of offence.</hi> So that the effect is not in the Preacher, but in the diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed auditour. Laſtly, that a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet muſt aſwell denounce Gods iudgements, as pronounce his
<pb facs="tcp:3045:37"/>
mercies. So did <hi>Hoſheah</hi> to the <hi>Clergie,</hi> when he cried, <hi>O ye Prieſts,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hoſ. 5. 1.</note> 
               <hi>heare this:</hi> and to the <hi>Laitie, Harken O ye houſe of Iſrael:</hi> and to the kings Court, <hi>Giue eare O houſe of the king: for iudgement is toward you, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe yee haue beene a ſnare in Miz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pah, &amp; a net ſpred vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Tabor.</hi> In like manner alſo doe al the Prophets. Fitly therefore heere doth <hi>Chriſt Ieſus, the very ſpirit of Prophecy,</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claime the wicked world to bee excepted in his holy and heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly mediation. He therefore ſaith, <hi>I pray not.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Durus eſt hic ſermo, quia cor no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrum durius.</hi> Did the ſunne ſtand ſtill at the praier of <hi>Ioſua?</hi> did it<note place="margin">Joſh. 10. 12 2. Reg. 20. 11. Mat. 26. 45.</note> retire ten degrees in the Dial of <hi>Ahas,</hi> at the word of <hi>Ezechias?</hi> And was it darkened at the paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>Chriſt Ieſus?</hi> No maruell then if now it had ſtood ſtill, and
<pb facs="tcp:3045:37" rendition="simple:additions"/>
neuer againe mooued, or retired to the vtmoſt corner of the world, and neuer returned, or beene vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly darkened, and neuer giuen a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny light againe, ſeeing the light of the world, and the Sonne of God ſaid, <hi>I pray not for the world.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ex. 19. 18.</note> Did Mount <hi>Sinay</hi> tremble at the giuing of the Law, and the walles<note place="margin">Ioſh. 6. 20</note> of <hi>Iericho fall downe,</hi> when the Prieſts ſounded their Trumpets? and did the earth quake at the paſſion of Ieſus Chriſt, as fain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting vnder ſuch an hideous bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then,<note place="margin">Mat. 26. 51</note> that the wicked and accur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed ſonnes of men ſhould execute the Lord of life? No maruell then if the whole frame and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brik of heauen &amp; of earth had not beene diſſolued into their ancient <hi>Chaos,</hi> when <hi>Chriſt Ieſus</hi> by whom all things were made, ſhall ſay, <hi>I pray not for the world.</hi> But the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens
<pb facs="tcp:3045:38"/>
&amp; the earth are reſerued vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to<note place="margin">2. Pet. 3. 7.</note> the ſecond and glorious com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of the Lord, and are now preſerued, and ſuſteined only for the good of the elect, for whoſe ſake onely this world continueth, that their number may bee full, and accrue vnto the Lord. Bleſſed be the maieſtie of our God for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uermore.</p>
            <p>But O Lord, may we be ſo bold as to enquire a reaſon why thou that diddeſt ſacrifice thy ſelfe for the ſinnes of the world, wilt not pray for the world? Surely (bleſſed and beloued in the Lord) I will not conceale that from you which the Lord hath reuealed: He praieth not for the world, the firſt reaſon may be drawne from a mandatorie prohibition. The ſecond from the Communion of Saints. The third from diſtincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb facs="tcp:3045:38" rendition="simple:additions"/>
of diuine knowledge, and the fourth from Chriſts owne fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge. Firſt therefore as<note place="margin">Mat. 12.</note> there is a ſinne irremiſſible, ſo there are ſinners not to be pardo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned nor prayed for. Concerning which ſinne, the prohibition is,<note place="margin">1. Ioh. 5. 16,</note> 
               <hi>There is a ſinne vnto death. I ſay not</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Cor. 4 4</note> 
               <hi>that thou ſhouldeſt pray for it.</hi> Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, it is ſaid, <hi>That the Deuill is the God of this world.</hi> What Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion then hath Chriſt with <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lial,</hi> or light with darkeneſſe?<note place="margin">1. Ioh. 5. 19</note> Thirdly, GOD hath giuen this knowledge vnto his Children, that they know themſelues to be of God, <hi>and the whole world lieth in wickedneſſe.</hi> What then hath<note place="margin">1. Cor. 4. 9. 13.</note> Chriſt to doe with the ſtoole of wickedneſſe? Fourthly, Chriſt foreſaw that this world ſhould murther his Saints, &amp; <hi>make the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the gazing ſtocke of the world, &amp; account</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:3045:39"/>
               <hi>them as the riffe raffe of the world,</hi> and treade them vnder foote, <hi>as the of <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>couring of all things.</hi> Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, Chriſt foreſaw that the wicked world ſhould deale more cruelly with the coate of maintenance of the <hi>Church,</hi> then did the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Souldiers with Chriſts coat, who caſt lots for it; but this world di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uides, and rents, and teares it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to peeces, and well is he that can get a peece, albeit it profiteth him not: nay, although all the reſt he hath be curſed for it. That coat which the ſouldiers caſt lots for, was without ſeame, wouen from the top to the bottome. The ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers were wiſe, who ſaw if it were diuided, it would roue, and be to no benefit; they therefore became aduenturers, who ſhould haue all. But this politike world which ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth to deuoure religion, delaieth
<pb facs="tcp:3045:39" rendition="simple:additions"/>
not the time in lotterie, but euery one ſnatcheth and catcheth, ſome by violence, as wilde beaſts and Boares of the forreſt, and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morants of the world: ſome by craft and ſubtiltie, as Foxes nip the bloſſoms of the Lords vine, vntill it die againe. Thirdly, <hi>Chriſt</hi> foreſaw that the wretched world ſhould not onely vnmannerlie exclude the Lord of life out of doore, albeit hee knocketh and deſireth entrance, but alſo that it wold deale clowniſhly with him, as did the inhumane <hi>Gergeſens,</hi> who willed him to depart out of their Coaſts.</p>
            <p>The vſe of this exception is, that wee enter into no aſſociati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and leagues with this wicked world, for it is deliuered vp into three fearefull traditions, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther deſertions. Firſt, vnto the
<pb facs="tcp:3045:40"/>
luſts of a wicked heart. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, vnto vile affections. Thirdly,<note place="margin">Rom. 1.</note> into a reprobate ſenſe. The <hi>Pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mograph</hi> therfore bids vs <hi>haue no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to doe with the ſtoole of wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, which imagineth miſchiefe as a Law.</hi> And the Apoſtle proclai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth the Lords will, ſaying, <hi>Come</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Cor. 6. 17. 18.</note> 
               <hi>out from among them, and ſeperate your ſelues</hi> (ſaith the Lord) <hi>and touch none vncleane things, and I will receiue you, and I will be a father vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you, and you ſhall bee my Sonnes and daughters, ſaith the Lord Almightie.</hi> But let vs conſider farther: Firſt, who are here deſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by the world, and ſecondlie why they are ſo deſcribed. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the firſt, who are ſignified by the world.</p>
            <p>As the paſſion of Chriſt: ſo the praier of Chriſt ſufficient for all, but not effectuall to all: ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient
<pb facs="tcp:3045:40" rendition="simple:additions"/>
for all, it is the current of the fathers. That one drop of the blood of the ſonne of God, was ſufficient to expiate the ſinnes of the whole world<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but albeit, the ſonne of God did ſweate bloud in an Agonie, yea, not drops, but clots of bloud, and that in ſuch quantitie, that it trickled downe to the ground, to bleſſe the earth, which was accurſed: Yea, and ſeas of pretious bloud iſſued in his glorious paſſion from his hands and feete, yea, and from his verie heart, yet there is a curſed and wretched<note place="margin">He. 10. 29.</note> generation, which treade vnder foote the Sonne of God, and count the bloud of the Teſtament as an vnholy thing, &amp; deſpiſe the ſpirit of grace. Of theſe the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Apoſtle telleth the Church<note place="margin">Phil. 3<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 18. 19.</note> of <hi>Philippi</hi> weeping, <hi>That they are</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:3045:41"/>
               <hi>are the enemies of the croſſe of Chriſt, whoſe God is their bellie, whoſe glorie is their ſhame, whoſe end is fearefull damnation, which minde worldly things.</hi> Rightly therefore are they deſigned by the world.</p>
            <p>So doe the ancient interpret <hi>world.</hi> For I will not detaine you with the manifold acceptions of this word <hi>world,</hi> and the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſcuous vſage thereof. <hi>I pray not for the world:</hi> That is, ſaith <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard,</hi> for them that wholly addict and addreſſe themſelues to the world: <hi>I pray not for the world.</hi> That is, ſaith <hi>Ierome,</hi> for the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, and euill men of the world. <hi>I pray not for the world:</hi> That is, ſaith <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> for theſe that fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low and purſue the concupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcence of the fleſh. In all this wee may inferre, that the world here is directly oppoſed to the diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples,
<pb facs="tcp:3045:41" rendition="simple:additions"/>
and followers of Chriſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus: and ſo Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> taketh the world in his Goſpell, where hee ſaith, <hi>Chriſt came into the world, and</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iohn. 1. 10</note> 
               <hi>the world receiued him not.</hi> So that nothing can be more contrariant to Chriſt and true Chriſtians, then theſe that are heere deſigned by the world: which will appeare vnto vs moſt euidently in the part following, wherein wee may exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine the reſemblance why they are ſignified by the world. Which is, firſt, in reſpect of the parts. Secondly, in regard of the cauſe<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of the world. Firſt, in the parts, both Firmamentarie, and Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentary.</p>
            <p>In the Firmamentarie parts of the world, they are fitly reſembled vnto the Eclipſes and Meteors. In the Elementarie parts to their corruption and rebellion. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb facs="tcp:3045:42"/>
in the cauſes, to two onely: the Materiall, and the formall cauſe. As for the other, as they know not, ſo they care not to know or conſider.</p>
            <p>But let vs returne to the Firma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentary part. In the Firmamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary world, there bee Eclipſes of Sunne and moone. For wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as the Moone receiueth her light from the ſunne, it hapneth that in the full, the Moone being in the head or taile of the Dragon vnder the <hi>Madix</hi> of the ſunne, that the<note place="margin">Iohannes de Sacro buſto de Sphaera.</note> earth will be enterpoſed between the ſunne and the Moone, ſo that the ſhadowe of the earth falling vpon the bodie of the Moone, cauſeth her not to bee ſeene in our ſight. Such is the Eclipſe of the wicked in this world. For by the Moone is reſembled the church, which is alwaies eclipſed
<pb facs="tcp:3045:42" rendition="simple:additions"/>
vnto the vngodly, by the ſhadow of earthly things, for they are put betweene their ſight, and the Church. So ſaith <hi>Saint Paul. If our</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Cor. 4. 4.</note> 
               <hi>Goſpell bee hid, it is hid to them that are loſt, in whom the God of this world hath blinded the mindes of the infidels, that the light of the glorious Goſpell of Chriſt, which is the Image of God, ſhould not ſhine vnto them.</hi> Note, that the God of this world blindeth them, and ſo they ſuffer a fearefull eclipſe. The Sunne is<note place="margin">Idem in tract. de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſphaera.</note> eclipſed when the bodie of the Moone is interpoſed betweene our ſight and the bodie of the Sunne, not that the Sunne loſeth any light, but is therby ſhadowed from our ſight. In like manner, the ſonne of GOD is eclipſed to the wicked worldlings by the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence that they take of the church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es meaneneſſe. This is apparent
<pb facs="tcp:3045:43"/>
by the ſpeech of the <hi>Phariſies, Doth</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 7. 48. 49.</note> 
               <hi>any of the Rulers or the Phariſies be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue in him? but this people which know not the law are accurſed.</hi> The offence they take at the church is the meannes &amp; deiection therof, which yet is confirmed by our <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour, That the poore receiue the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell.</hi> Fitly alſo are they reſembled by the Meteors: for the <hi>Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ariſtot. de meteor. l. 1.</note> tearme them the paſſions of the Elements, ſo likewiſe are theſe diſtemperatures of the world. In the Church they are <hi>Heretikes</hi> and <hi>Schiſmatikes:</hi> In the Common-wealth <hi>Traitors</hi> and <hi>Combuſtions:</hi> In ſocieties and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porations, the fire brands of hell and diſſenſion. They are Meteors of euerie element: of the fire, as tailed <hi>Meteors;</hi> for if they bee great and honourable in the world, they draw a great traine
<pb facs="tcp:3045:43" rendition="simple:additions"/>
with them of <hi>Seruitors</hi> and <hi>Retai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners,</hi> all which muſt bee at their beck, and inſiſt in the ſteps of their inſolencie and diuelliſh policie, many of which ſort of <hi>Meteors</hi> do fall from the firmament, and ſo do theſe, and the fal of them is great. And ſome of theſe Meteors are not indeed of the fire, but ſeeme to bee, hauing in them neither <hi>il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumination</hi> nor heat, but onelie a falſe glimmering, and theſe the <hi>Naturaliſts</hi> call <hi>ignes fatui,</hi> walking fires in the night ſeaſon. So theſe wretched worldlings haue no goodneſſe neither <hi>effectiuè</hi> nor <hi>formaltier,</hi> neither in themſelues reallie, nor towards others in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed and verilie, but onely a falſe and feigned gloſſe of goodneſſe &amp; hypocriſie. Like alſo to the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teors of the Ayre: For <hi>Bernard</hi> calleth them <hi>venti furentes,</hi> raging
<pb facs="tcp:3045:44"/>
and bluſtering winds, throwing downe, and violently ouertur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning whatſoeuer occurreth them. And <hi>Auguſtine</hi> calleth them <hi>venti</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. in ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liloquio.</note> 
               <hi>adurentes,</hi> windes ſcorching and drying vp by their vnthankful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, the chryſtall ſtreame of Gods mercie and grace, which would flow vnto them. Like al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo vnto the watrie Meteors, euen to thoſe <hi>Nubes pendulae,</hi> which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe raine, but giue neither drop nor dew. So <hi>Saint Iude</hi> ſtileth them, <hi>Clouds they are without water</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iude 12.</note> 
               <hi>carried about of euerie winde.</hi> Laſtly among the Meteors of the earth, to lead are they reſembled by the Prophet, for he ſaith, <hi>Iniquitie is as</hi>
               <note place="margin">Zac. 5. 7. 8.</note> 
               <hi>a talent of lead,</hi> which if they doe not looke vnto, it will weigh and ſway them downe to the bottom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe pit of hell, and heauineſſe. You ſee now how fitly the wicked
<pb facs="tcp:3045:44" rendition="simple:additions"/>
are reſembled to the eclipſes, and <hi>Meteors</hi> of the firmamentarie world. Now let vs deſcend vnto the <hi>Elementarie:</hi> and heerein they are like vnto them in their cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption and rebellion. Firſt vnto the fire in vnkinde blaſtings: ſo theſe in their wilfull and wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed blaſphemies. Secondly, vnto the Aire, when it infecteth: ſo they by their euill examples and miſperſwaſions, corrupt and taint all thoſe which are neare vnto them. Thirdly, as the water by vncouth and vnvſual inundations doth runne ouer the land, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroieth both the corne and cat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tel: ſo doe theſe cormorants and wretched worldlings depopulate whole countries by encloſures, &amp; by racking their miſerable te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants. Laſtly, they are fitly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> vnto the Briers and
<pb facs="tcp:3045:45"/>
Thornes of the earth: for the ſpirit of God ſaith, <hi>as is the Lilly amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g the thornes, ſo is my ſpouſe among the</hi>
               <note place="margin">Can. 2. 2.</note> 
               <hi>daughters.</hi> As for the cauſes of the world, they know but two, &amp; ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after they work accordingly. The 1. is, the material cauſe. They hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pilie credit and deeme the world to bee made of nothing: for they deſire to reduce and bring it, and themſelues to nothing. And in li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing here without <hi>Chriſt,</hi> it to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; they to it, are nothing, for aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as <hi>without him was made no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing.</hi> For if a worldling be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uote,<note place="margin">Ioh. 1. 3.</note> his religion is an <hi>Idoll, and an</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 8. 4.</note> 
               <hi>Idoll is nothing in this world:</hi> and if hee bee irreligious, and an <hi>Atheiſt,</hi> his bellie is his God, and the end thereof is <hi>faeda annihilatio,</hi> filthie nothing. This being the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence betweene a ſuperſtitious<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Plutarch.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> perſon &amp; an <hi>Atheiſt,</hi> the one <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:3045:45" rendition="simple:additions"/>
thinks there is no God: the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, wiſheth there were no God to puniſh his Idolatrie, ſo that the world to them, and they to themſelues are nothing: Their life onely beeing a meere phanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, and their liuelihood a meere fopperie. And as the world is ſaid to be round, which is the formall cauſe, ſo theſe wretches run arou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d temporizing in the world, doing. <note n="a" place="margin">Omnia pro tempore, ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hil pro ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritate.</note> 
               <hi>Al things to fit the time, nothing for the truth.</hi> 
               <note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Optat. li. 1 <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Chryſoſt</hi> 2. Tim. 3. 7</note> 
               <hi>Alwaies about the way, neuer in the way:</hi> like thoſe ſilly wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men that <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaketh of, <hi>Who are euer learning, and neuer come to the acknowledgement of the truth.</hi> For if you reſpect their practiſe, they are like vnto the Hedge-hog which hath two holes, one toward the <hi>South,</hi> the other toward the <hi>North,</hi> and when the winde blow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in the <hi>north,</hi> ſhe ſhutteth that,
<pb facs="tcp:3045:46"/>
and openeth the other toward the <hi>South,</hi> and turneth her ſelfe that way. If the winde blow in the <hi>South,</hi> ſhee openeth that to the <hi>North,</hi> and that way repoſeth her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe. Semblably doe theſe, for with euerie winde they turne, and with euery note tune according<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie. If you reſpect their heart, it is like the cart wheele which al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies turneth round in the dirt; ſo their affections are turmoiled in the vileſt and baſeſt conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. If you mark their thoughts, they are like a rowling axe-tree, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer deuiſing miſchief and miſerie euen vpon their beds: for there is no pece to the wicked. In a word, if you conſider their whole life, it is like vnto a Mil-horſe, euer mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing round, and neuer going for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, but at night in the ſame place as in the morning: ſo theſe,
<pb facs="tcp:3045:46" rendition="simple:additions"/>
as religious, as godly, as well diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed at thirtie as at twentie, at ſixtie, as at ſixteen: at the euening of their death, as at the morning of their birth.</p>
            <p>And for other cauſes beſides theſe two, they neither know nor deſire to learne. For as touching the efficient cauſe which is God, they haue ſaid with the curſed in <hi>Iob: Depart from vs, wee deſire not the knowledge of thy waies.</hi> And as for the enforcing cauſe which mooued God to make the world,<note place="margin">Iob. 21.</note> which was his goodnes, they bid the Lord keep the heauen to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, for they purpoſe not to trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble him; as for the earth, it is their portion, and they are content therewith. Concerning the inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall cauſe, whereby the Lord made the world, which was the perſonall Word, the Sonne of
<pb facs="tcp:3045:47"/>
God Chriſt Ieſus. They are like to the Diſciples of <hi>Epheſus, Who had</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 19. 2.</note> 
               <hi>not heard whether there were an holy Ghoſt or no.</hi> So theſe haue not heard whether there bee a Ieſus Chriſt or no; or if they did heare, they regarded it not. And laſtly for the finall cauſe, wherfore God made the world, that herein men ſhould ſerue and glorifie him, they are either mad with <hi>Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>docles,</hi> that there ſhall bee more and more worlds; or dote with <hi>Democritus,</hi> that this world was <hi>ex Contingenti,</hi> and ſo by chance and chaffer, they do &amp; deuiſe al their buſineſſe whiles they are in the world.</p>
            <p>Theſe are ſuch as Chriſt prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not for, foraſmuch as they ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſpeake of him, or thinke on him. But it may bee verified of<note place="margin">Grafion in his Chron<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> them, as Queene <hi>Mary</hi> ſaid of
<pb facs="tcp:3045:47" rendition="simple:additions"/>
herſelf lying vpon her death-bed, to her friends and comforters, that if they did rip her when ſhee was dead, they ſhould ſee <hi>Callis</hi> ſtamped in her heart, intimating that ſhe conceiued ſuch ſorrow at the loſſe of <hi>Callis,</hi> that it pearced her heart and killed her. So theſe are in ſuch loue with this world, that they onely heare it, they talke and thinke onely thereon, that if they were opened, you ſhould ſee the world engrauen and written in their hearts. But this is the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the world, <hi>That light</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iohn 3. 19.</note> 
               <hi>is come into it, and men loue darkenes more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> light.</hi> Yet be you of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort all yee bleſſed and beloued of the Lord, <hi>for you ſhall be the Iudges</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 6. 1.</note> 
               <hi>of this world.</hi> And with the reſidue Saint <hi>Iames</hi> ſhall expoſtulate: and ſo I will co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>clude the examination of the reſembance why the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked
<pb facs="tcp:3045:48"/>
are likened to the world. <hi>O ye</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iam. 4. 4.</note> 
               <hi>adulterers and adultereſſes, doe yee not know that the amity of the world is the emnitie of God. Whoſoeuer there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore will bee a friend of the world, maketh himſelfe the enemie of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And is not this world wherein wee now liue full fraught with ſuch enemies of God? Is not this the world that <hi>Chriſt praied not for?</hi> behold, the ataxie and diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of all things. The laſt Lords day from this place, you heard the plea of the Lord againſt this age of the world, and this land, wherin is no truth nor mercy, <hi>but</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hoſ. 4. 1. 2.</note> 
               <hi>ſwearing and lying, and killing, and ſtealing, and whoring, with breaking out, and blood toucheth blood:</hi> now you heare the reaſon thereof, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe theſe are the people whom the Lord Chriſt praieth not for.
<pb facs="tcp:3045:48" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Hence is it that the life of ſome is a loathſome ſtie of impuritie and impietie, and they lie wallowing in the dung and draft of their ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful filthineſſe. Of others, their life is a <hi>Corban</hi> of vniuſt guiles, which they falſlie call <hi>Gaines.</hi> And of others, whoſe life is an <hi>Acheldama</hi> of blood and oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, for they care not who wants nor ſtarue, ſo they may epicurize, gourmandize, &amp; ſpend it on their vaine and vile luſts, and wilfull af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections. But alas, what doe I in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to capitulate the wretched<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of this time and age, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in we now liue, which is rather to bee deteſted then commemora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, eſpecially ſeeing a godly bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther did ſo earneſtly &amp; ſo ferue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly touch and taxe the particulars the laſt Lords day? to which I referre your remembrance, and at this
<pb facs="tcp:3045:49"/>
time onelie deſire you to looke to one onelie miſchiefe and villanie, whereof this world is too too guiltie, and wherein it doth di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectlie oppoſe the <hi>Church of Chriſt Ieſus,</hi> and ſubiects it ſelfe to this feareful exception, <hi>that Chriſt prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not for it.</hi> And that is in thoſe things which are conſecrated by well diſpoſed mindes out of the world, to the ſeruice of the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie.</p>
            <p>The miſerie whereof, and my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterie of vngodlineſſe now buſily worketh, and is ſeene, firſt, in this worlds affection toward God in the things that belong vnto him. And ſecondly, in the vſe thereof intended to perpetuitie. For the firſt: The affection of the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer world hath beene to giue the beſt things to God: ſo did <hi>Abel giue</hi> of the fat of the earth in his
<pb facs="tcp:3045:49" rendition="simple:additions"/>
deuotions vnto the Lord; and <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon</hi> the flowre of euery ſacrifice: yea, the very heathen obſerued in their Idolatrous worſhip, to giue the things that were, Firſt, <hi>Pura,</hi> without blemiſh: Secondly, <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ba,</hi> ſound, Thirdly, <hi>Profana,</hi> not giuen before: And laſtly, <hi>Sua,</hi> truely their owne. But the affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of this world is cleane conrra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riant. For in dedicating your children to the Lord, if they bee deformed or fooliſh, then yee ſay they are good enough to become <hi>Prieſts.</hi> Of our yeeres, the worſt we giue to God, as our old and withered age; as for the flower of our life, wee wholly addreſſe that to the ſlauery of Satan, to ſpend it in vanitie and wantonneſſe, coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting it a preiudice to our youth, &amp; a diſparagement to our eſtate, to giue our ſelues to our beads be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb facs="tcp:3045:50"/>
wee bee decrepit, and good for nothing elſe. And as for the things wee offer vnto the Lord, yee make choice of the worſt, the vncleaneſt, the vnſoundeſt, or ſome pittance perhaps of a great maſſe which yee haue vniuſtly ſcraped, or violently, or craftily gotten, of other mens goods. Or elſe ſome taking a poore remorſe of what infinite wealth, he hath robbed the Church of, doth in his miſerable pitie beſtow ſome part of her own vpon her again, and thinketh he hath bound God vnto him, to bee beholding vnto his bountie for euer. And this, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued in the Lord, is the affection of this world, vnto the glorie and ſeruice of the moſt High.</p>
            <p>Now as touching the vſe which is intended to perpetuitie, two things are principallie to bee no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.
<pb facs="tcp:3045:50" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Firſt, are Temples built for the publike ſeruice of God: and ſecondly, the endowments of <hi>Churches;</hi> and reuenewes for the maintenance and perpetuating of that ſacred ſeruice: not that the Lord of heauen &amp; of earth wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth any thing that we haue, but this is his ordinance whereby wee may and ought to be exerciſed in the imploiment of thoſe things, wherewith hee bleſſeth vs to the promotion of his glorious ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice. Concerning Temples, the <hi>Elders</hi> of the Iewes thought they could not come to our Sauiour with a more forcible motiue, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they intreated for the Centurion,<note place="margin">Luk. 7. 5. 6.</note> then to ſay, <hi>He is worthy thou ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt doe this for him, for hee hath loued our nation, and hath built vs a Synagogue.</hi> Few either are in this our age, for whom wee may thus
<pb facs="tcp:3045:51"/>
pleade: but it it<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> bee in the buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of a fine houſe, or the deui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of ſundrie vanities and foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh pleaſures<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> thouſands are thought little enough to bee beſtowed. Witneſſe thoſe mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folde fabrikes, and ſtructures in this land, whereof many ſeueralls haue buried as much treaſure as would erect and found ſeuerall collegiat or cathedrall Churches. This age therefore wherein wee liue, admiring all theſe Temples and Colleges which are built, and ſee none built now doe ſay and often affirme, looking but vppon one of our Churches, <hi>If this were now to bee built, the whole land could not erect the ſame.</hi> Whereas if they caſt their eies vpon the houſes of many Noble men, Knights and meane gentlemen, they might ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſille diſcerne where the affection
<pb facs="tcp:3045:51" rendition="simple:additions"/>
reſteth. For you ſhall ſee their houſes like pallaces aduanced vp to heauen pompous—and ſpecious to behold, euerie ſmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>key chimney ouertopping, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerpeering the Lords temple, which happily obſcurely ſtands ſtooping and drooping beceath like a rude heape of ſtones, being made the receptacles of Owles and Oſtritches, <hi>Zim Ohim,</hi> &amp; dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing <hi>Satyres.</hi> Or if they would look vpon the vain maskes and ſhews and frantik pleaſures vpon which thouſands are imployed, to driue away the darkneſſe and teadiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of winter, they might eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conceiue that this woful world is directly oppoſed to God, and al holy goodneſſe. This is contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie to <hi>Dauids</hi> affection, for it was his heart greefe that hee might not dwell in the Courtes of the
<pb facs="tcp:3045:52"/>
Lords houſe, and it was his eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall wiſh, <hi>That he might beholde the beauty of the Temple of the Lord.</hi> And this is alſo far different from the deuotion of the chriſtian <hi>Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perors</hi> and eſtates of the primatiue Church, who erected <hi>Churches,</hi> built <hi>Colleges</hi> &amp; <hi>Schooles,</hi> endow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them with maintenance, and left them to poſteritie, and they like cormorants haue deuoured the church reuenues, and left the children thereof to liue like <hi>Gide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> ſouldiers in the lapping cold water.</p>
            <p>Furthermore, as concerning<note place="margin">Iudg. 7. 6</note> the endowments of the Church, this world holdes it as a granted propoſition, that <hi>non oportet chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtum diteſc<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re.</hi> Contrarie to the practiſe of the firſt church, which was founded and framed by the finger of God, whether you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect
<pb facs="tcp:3045:52" rendition="simple:additions"/>
it in the tabernacle or in the temple. In time of the tabernacle being yet in the deſert, the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narie treaſure of the Church was 2400. ſhekels of ſiluer, and 120. ſhekels of golde, euerie ſhekell weighing halfe an ounce. Yea, the treaſurie was euen then a <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo ſcit,</hi> as may be gathered out of the booke of <hi>Numbers.</hi> The treaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of the temple was valued to be at one time laid vp in ſtore 8000. <hi>Cichars</hi> of golde, and ſeuenteene thouſand <hi>Cichars</hi> of ſiluer, euerie <hi>Cichar</hi> weighing 1800. ſhekels, beſide the oblations and gifts at the building againe of the temple in the time of <hi>Nehemias.</hi> Yea eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the time of <hi>Sanhedrim, Mithri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dates</hi> had at one time 800. talents<note place="margin">Cic. orat. pro L. Flac Ioſeph. an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiq. l. 14. c. 12</note> of treaſure of the temple, as <hi>Cicero</hi> in his Oration for <hi>Flacous</hi> recor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth. And <hi>Craſſus</hi> a Roman Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine
<pb facs="tcp:3045:53"/>
had at another time of <hi>Elea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zar</hi> the Prieſt, a beame of treaſure weighing 700. talents and more, as <hi>Ioſephus</hi> teſtifieth. But what do I inſiſt vpon the Iewiſh <hi>Churches</hi> treaſurie, ſeeing the Chriſtian <hi>Church</hi> affordeth ſo pregna<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie how diueliſh this deuice of the world is, &amp; that the end ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of (as of the poſſeſſed) is worſe then the beginning. But I may not longer detaine you with loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king far backe. Recount but from the time of King <hi>Edward</hi> the firſt, when the world was inforced to enact the ſtatute of <hi>Mortmaine,</hi> whereby it was prouided that none ſhould giue to the <hi>church</hi> without an eſpecial licence from the king: which ſtatute is yet vnrepealed, but I thinke it may bee repealed without preiudice to the Kings Crowne, or dignity, or diſparage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb facs="tcp:3045:53" rendition="simple:additions"/>
to the ſtate, ſeeing the affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions &amp; diſpoſitions of this world are not toward the Church, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe it bee in ſome good words from ſome certaine ſpecious word-mongers. But what may be the cauſe that many of the hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of the <hi>Nobilitie</hi> and gentrie of this Land, proſper not, nor beare the part &amp; honour that their fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fathers did, ſeeing ſome haue at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempted al meanes both direct &amp; vndirect to adua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce their fortunes to the vtmoſt? as namely: Firſt, by improuements, and racking of Tenants, that <hi>Ieſuiticall</hi> deuice, &amp; popiſh practiſe, ſaluing it with this hypocriticall plaiſter: <hi>It is lawful for euery man to make the moſt of his owne.</hi> Whereby they ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour to ſhadow al their vnconſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onable, and vnchriſtian dealings. Secondly, by the fauours of their
<pb facs="tcp:3045:54"/>
prince, which hath not a little lif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vp the conditions of ſome. Thirdly, by all forfeitures, morga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, perpetuall ſuites &amp; turmoiles in the law, wreſting it out of the handes and hearts of the lawful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie poſſeſſed. And laſtly by their practiſe in claiming from the Church, by impropriations, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cealements, fraudes, and other in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite ſtrange deuices and practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes. And yet all this will not ſerue, but they are yet more gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die then before, and farre more needy then their ancient<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ie. Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, beloued and bleſſed in the Lord Ieſus, I know no other cauſe but this: your fore-fathers were neuer wel but when they were be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinking themſelues what they ſhould giue vnto the Church and maintenance of the Goſpell of <hi>Chriſt Ieſus,</hi> and therefore GOD
<pb facs="tcp:3045:54" rendition="simple:additions"/>
bleſſed all that they poſſeſſed: but you as directly contrarie, ſeek by all meanes to haue from the Church you care not how; wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of it commeth that all you haue is thereby accurſed, neither can you enioy it. Doe you ſee a <hi>Repreſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue Church</hi> vpon the earth? who founded it? did not your proge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitors? If the ſame minde had beene in them, which is in you, what face or faſhion of a Church had there beene at this day in the Chriſtian world? Nay, further<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more, becauſe couetouſnes, and <hi>Prodigalitie</hi> cannot ſweepe ſtake with the Churches goods in that poore remainder which is left, after which the world yet moſt greedily gapeth, and vnſatiablie luſteth, the Sonnes of religion ſtand vp like the agents and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uocates of deſperation, and plead
<pb facs="tcp:3045:55"/>
that the fulneſſe of bread hath made the Church to wantonize, therefore they muſt be ſo bold as to take it from them, for feare they ſhould ſurfeit. And further, that <hi>Endowments hath poiſoned reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion,</hi> and therefore they haue pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared an <hi>Antidote.</hi> And laſtly, that our hearts and affections we may beſtow vpon God, but as for our goods, wee may imploy them o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe, yea any waies they think well, but to the <hi>Church</hi> and Gods word: So that you ſee now (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued) the worldlings themſelues feare not to ſurfet and die with fulneſſe, nor to be poiſoned with theſe <hi>Endowments,</hi> but ſuch is their charitie and care of Gods Church, that they would not it ſhould thus miſcarrie, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they will carry what they may from it. Hence is it that your
<pb facs="tcp:3045:55" rendition="simple:additions"/>
faith is ſo little, that were our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour liuing on earth, hee might truely ſay vnto you, <hi>O yee of little Faith.</hi> For what tokens remaine of your being Chriſtians in this world? but euen as the curſed complaine, their life is like a ſhip that paſſeth through the water, &amp; maketh a noiſe with the violence of winde, carrying her ſailes, but when ſhee is paſt, no token re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maines of her paſſage: or as a bird that flieth, parteth indeed the aire with her wings, and ſwift flying, and as an arrow which is ſhot at a marke, leaueth no token or note of their going through, ſo your life is ſpent in a dreame, and you leaue no print or ſignification that you haue liued thankfully to your God. Hence is it that your hope is leſſe, either being like the vaine hope of <hi>Abſolon,</hi> who reared
<pb facs="tcp:3045:56"/>
vp a pillar in the kings dale, ſo you ſome pompous <hi>Pyramis,</hi> or gay tabernacle of clay in the earth: or like the hope of the Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrite, which is reſembled to the flowre of the poppie, which euery blaſt ſcattereth, ſo all your hope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full proiects in this world, are pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtrated by euery blaſt and tempeſt of aduerſe caſualtie. Hence is it that your charitie is leſſe then lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, either toward God, or toward your Brethren. Frſt, toward God. Heretofore the King of the earth came to Cottages of the men of God, and called them Fathers, <hi>Oh</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. King. 13. 14.</note> 
               <hi>my Father, my Father, the Chariots of Aegypt, and the horſe-men of the ſame.</hi> But now the ſeruants of Chriſt muſt bee ſuters to the vaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſailes of Princes, to bee admitted vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Secondly, towards your brethren, nothing but enuie, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice,
<pb facs="tcp:3045:56" rendition="simple:additions"/>
and all vncharitableneſſe, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt which we may truely pray, as the Church doth, <hi>Good Lord de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuer vs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The concluſion then, if you wil be pleaſed attentiuely to hearken, yea, but a very little, ſhall inſtant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly follow in this one illatiue, <hi>That whatſoeuer is in this world, if it be not enioyed in Chriſt Ieſus, is anathema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized and accurſed.</hi> A view heere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of we may behold in <hi>Iericho:</hi> at the ſacking of which citie, <hi>Ioſhua</hi> is en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyned to beware of the execra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble thing; for the whole citie and all therein was accurſed, ſauing that onely which was conſecrated to the Lord: and the thing was not onely execrable in it ſelfe, but it made them alſo accurſed that touched it. Semblably are all the thinges of this world, which are poſſeſſed without Chriſt, execra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble,
<pb facs="tcp:3045:57"/>
both in their poſſeſſion, vſe, imployment, and end, and the ow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners alſo thereby anathematized. What then, beloued in the Lord,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 10. 11.</note> ſhall we doe, <hi>vpon whom the ends of the world are fallen?</hi> The ſpirit of God hath not left vs either<note place="margin">1. Cor. 7. 8</note> comfortles or councelleſſe. <hi>Pauls</hi> counſell and exhortation is, <hi>Vſe the world as if you vſed it not,</hi> and that both in action and affection, not in action, no not ſo much as<note place="margin">Rom. 12. 2.</note> in faſhion. <hi>Faſhion not your ſelues like vnto this world:</hi> for you ſee the faſhio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of this world hath vndone many, and cauſed them to forget God their Creator, their countrie and comely faſhion, yea, them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues and their poſteritie, ſo ſicke and frantike haue many beene of the faſhions of this world, which are accurſed, as it is apparant by their witleſſe and wicked ends,
<pb facs="tcp:3045:57" rendition="simple:additions"/>
who haue turned themſelues in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all faſhions like the <hi>Camelian,</hi> ſaue the good and honeſt faſhion.</p>
            <p>Neither in your affection cleaue vnto the world. For the beloued Diſciple forbids you <hi>to loue the</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Ioh. 2. 15</note> 
               <hi>world or any thing therein,</hi> vnleſſe your loue be in God, and for his ſake. The reaſon he yeeldeth, is, a map or view of the world, which hee capitulateth in a <hi>Hypotheſis.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Io. 2. 16</note> 
               <hi>If any loue the world, this loue of the father is not in him. For all that is in the world (as the luſt of the fleſh, the lust of the eies, and the pride of life) is not of the Father, but is of the world.</hi> And leſt either faſhion, which now is accounted the forme of the world, as if it gaue that being (for many thinke they are not, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe they bee in the formall faſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the world) or luſt, which is eſteemed the frame of the world,
<pb facs="tcp:3045:58"/>
ſhould annihilate or vilepend this diuine Councell, the ſpirit of God vrgeth further: Firſt, to the fanaticall faſhionable, <hi>That the</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 7. 3</note> 
               <hi>faſhion of this world vaniſheth:</hi> Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly,<note place="margin">1. Joh. 2. 17</note> to the luſtfull, <hi>That the world it ſelfe paſſeth away, and the luſt thereof.</hi> Will any obiect that this is but heareſay? Why then, attend to an eie witneſſe: <hi>I haue ſeene the wicked</hi> (ſaith <hi>Dauid) flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh like a greene Bay tree:</hi> (there is one in the faſhion) <hi>and I paſſed by, &amp; loe he was gone, &amp; his place knew him no more:</hi> ther's the fall of the faſhion. The life of theſe being a very dreame, <hi>euen like vnto a hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grie</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſa. 29. 8.</note> 
               <hi>man dreaming: for lo he eareth: and when he awaketh his ſoule is <gap reason="illegible" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptie: or like as a thirſtie ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dreameth, &amp; loe he drinketh, but when he awa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth, his ſoule is faintie.</hi> Euen ſo is the iſſue of faſhion and luſt,
<pb facs="tcp:3045:58" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>vanitie</hi> of ſtate, and <hi>Imbecillitie</hi> of ſtrength. Al the followers &amp; fauo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rites wherof put their gaines as the vnthriftie ſeruant did his ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings,<note place="margin">Hag. 1. 6.</note> euen into <hi>ſacculum pertuſum,</hi> a bottomleſſe bag, no ſooner in but out. Fitly therfore is the ſtate and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dition of this world reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled to <hi>Ionas gourde, quae ſtatim ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tim perijt.</hi> And Saint <hi>Paul</hi> conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth, <hi>That while we are in the bodie</hi> (that is attending the bodie onely as if wee had no ſoules) <hi>we wander</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Cor. 5. 4</note> 
               <hi>a Pilgrimage from the Lord. We muſt therefore pray that wee may goe out of the bodie, and ſo reſt with the Lord eternallie.</hi> But if <hi>Paul</hi> were in the fleſh, &amp; did preach this doctrine,<note place="margin">2. Tim. 4. 10.</note> yet <hi>Demas</hi> will forſake him, and <hi>Chriſt</hi> to, &amp; embrace this preſent world: as his deare darling, and ſole delight. Many and manifolde are the multitudes, which make
<pb facs="tcp:3045:59"/>
ſuch account of this world, that they can by no meanes be wooed from it, let the melanchollie ſchollers ſay what they will. And therefore is it that ſo many haue turned religion into pollicy, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by that prouerb is verified<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>The Daughter hath deuoured the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</hi> Religion hath bred peace, and peace praies and tires vpon religion. Hence is it that ſo many church-robbers, tyrannize vpon the reuenues and goods of the<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Danaeu<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n Apho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſm. Poli<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tic. lib. 1.</note> Church, being indeede no better, flatter themſelues how they luſt, but <hi>Pyrats</hi> by land mother mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therers and vſurpers of others goods. <hi>Pyrats</hi> by land more inhu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane and tyrannicall vnto the <hi>Chriſtian Church,</hi> then the <hi>Pyrats</hi> by <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ea <hi>Ward</hi> and <hi>Dansker</hi> to the<note place="margin">Report of <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ota<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>le p<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ts<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> Chriſtian common-wealth. Thoſe taking by open violence: theſe
<pb facs="tcp:3045:59" rendition="simple:additions"/>
encroching and entring by cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning practiſe &amp; ſiniſter pretence. Mother murtherers they are alſo. for if the church bee our mother and they take away the bread and liuely-hood from her, wherby ſhe fainteth, ſickneth, &amp; dieth. What are they but mother murtherers, and of the generation of <hi>Vipers?</hi> Laſtly, they are vſurpers of others goods: for he is a Vſurper that ap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>propriateth others goods vnto himſelfe. But theſe Church rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers do claime not onely intereſt but alſo lawfull poſſeſſion and vſe of Chriſts goods, in that they rob him in tythes and offerings which he calleth <hi>his,</hi> what are they then but Vſurpers, &amp; encrochers vpon others tenures and intereſt? But their precedent generation hath denounced a woe againſt ſaying, <hi>Woe be vnto them that either</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:3045:60"/>
               <hi>waſh or clippe the coine whereon the Lord hath ſet his ſtampe.</hi> Yea, your anceſtours commonly vſed theſe words in their donations: <hi>Let their</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ex aribi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uis <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>alleg Gland.</note> 
               <hi>accou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t be without fauor in the day of the Lord, whether they be our heires or ſucceſſors, who ſhall dare to dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh or alter the lands reuenues and inheritance that we haue conſecrated to the Lord.</hi> If the iudgement of your elders be required, this impi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and iniurious ſurpriſing of Church eſtates, hath beene con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned both by Chriſtian bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, and alſo by Chriſtian Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perors, who euer were willing ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to lay downe their liues, then that the proſperity of the church ſhould bee impeached, or the goods thereof wickedly imbea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zeled, or diuerted from the godly intendments of her well diſpoſed benefactors. But you ſee beloued
<pb facs="tcp:3045:60" rendition="simple:additions"/>
that <hi>Chriſts Church</hi> hath bene ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſed, and diſpoyled of her poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſions, that whereas the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> ſaith, <hi>The earth is the Lords,</hi> The men of the earth with their earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly mindes haue left our Lord, as the <hi>Iewes,</hi> no place to reſt his head ſo they, no land to ſet his foot vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon. Hence are your lacklatines, &amp; your lacklearnings which you fondly and furiouſlie obiect vnto the reuerent <hi>Beaupeers</hi> of the church, the Biſhops, whereas you your ſelues haue made ſuch prieſts by robbing the Church, as church-Pyrats by famiſhing the Church-men in taking away their bread and liuelihood, &amp; by vſurping the poſſeſſion of others. For who ſhould ſerue your foure pound, fiue pound, twentie no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles cures? if ſuch were not or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained to holde your plough,
<pb facs="tcp:3045:61"/>
your Church and pariſh would lie fallow, yea, that poor pittance which is left to maintaine a few better qualified perſons is ſo caught and dailie vndermined by bare weather beaten deſperate courtiers, forlorne Gentlemen, &amp; <hi>Cyclop<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cal</hi> ſcatizers, that al wiſdom &amp; godlie policie of the reuerend Biſhops and faithfull councellers of ſtate, vſing their beſt endeuors &amp; vtmoſt fidelitie is little enough to retaine it: ſo far are they from any hope of a ſucceſſion or godlie deuoted generation, who would ſtudie to promote the wealth of the Church.</p>
            <p>But let this generation know, that the world is giuen vp to a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probate ſenſe, and if they follow it, they alſo are in no better eſtate. Good Lord, where is the bleſſing and fruite of the ancient time?
<pb facs="tcp:3045:61" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Happie is he that preacheth to an attentiue eare, and to an intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent heart, and an obedient ſoule. Worthy <hi>Ridley</hi> in one ſermon to that famous renowned Chriſtian Prince <hi>Edward</hi> the ſixt, preuailed that <hi>Chriſt-Church</hi> hoſpitall, the Hoſpitall of Saint <hi>Bartholomews</hi> in <hi>Southwarke,</hi> and Bridewell were at once erected. But now in an hundred Sermons the miniſters of Chriſt, muſt become like to the Friars <hi>Mendicants,</hi> and yet not ſo far preuaile, euen in this place with this <hi>Hono.</hi> citie us to purchaſe entertainement. I hope I ſhall be the laſt that euer ſhall mention it. And to conclude (my bleſſed brethren) ſeeing that al the things of this world are accurſed with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <hi>Chriſt,</hi> ſe<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> before your eies <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Dauid</hi> as preſidents and motiues to exhort you to reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.
<pb facs="tcp:3045:62"/>
               <hi>Paul was crucified to the world</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gal. 6. 14.</note> 
               <hi>and the world to him, and accounted all things as loſſe and dung for the lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cre</hi>
               <note place="margin">Phil. 9. 8</note> 
               <hi>of Chriſt.</hi> And <hi>Dauid</hi> wondred <hi>That any man ſhould deſire ought in heauen but the Lord, or eſteeme any thing in earth, in reſpect of his God.</hi> Let vs not then bee like ſucking babes, who rather cleaue to their nurſe then to their owne naturall mother. This world is our drie nurſe, the <hi>Church</hi> is our true mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Let vs then that are able to receiue ſtrong meat, learne to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh. But if for al this you de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe this counſell, &amp; ſet at naught theſe aduertiſments, and addict your ſelues wholly to the world: liſten and heare how the world will deale with you in the end. Serue it neuer ſo long, yet as Churliſh <hi>Laban</hi> dealt with <hi>Iacob</hi> in bringing foule <hi>Leah</hi> to his ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage
<pb facs="tcp:3045:62" rendition="simple:additions"/>
bed inſteed of faire <hi>Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chel,</hi> ſo the world wil promiſe you gladſomnes, but will performe loathſomneſſe: will promiſe you the fineſt and gaieſt ſpeciouſnes, but will performe with you in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitfull ſpitefulnes. Let the expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rienced ſay, if by the world they found any thing but worldly care in gaining the world, wordly fear in retaining it, &amp; worldly ſorrow in loſing it. Yea, this is the meede of their life, and in their death in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteed of <hi>Tumulus</hi> giue them <hi>cumu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus,</hi> an heape of ſtones, as had <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chan,</hi> who touched the execrable thing, ſo theſe haue ſome painted Sepulcher, or ſome ſpecious or pompous funerall, and there is <hi>Cataſtrophe</hi> &amp; the guerde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that the world affords them. But you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued and bleſſed in the Lord, lift vp your hearts to him that prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
<pb facs="tcp:3045:63"/>
for you, in whome you are the Sonnes &amp; the ſaints, the <hi>Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces</hi> and <hi>Prieſts,</hi> the <hi>Beloued,</hi> and the <hi>Baptized,</hi> the <hi>Illuminates</hi> and <hi>Aſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciates</hi> of the higheſt: by whoſe ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings you are ſeperated and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhed with works of ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on from the reſidue of the world, &amp; through whom God dwelleth in you by the liuerie and ſeiſon of his gratious ſpirit in this life, and will after this life is ended, be in full poſſeſſion of you both in ſoule and bodie eternallie in the glorious reſt of heauen.</p>
            <p>To moue you now therfore to are ſolution to leaue this world, &amp; all worldly, fleſhly, and diueliſh practiſes of the worldlings, and ſuch as are <hi>ex diamet<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o contrariant</hi> to all heartie and vnfained Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, &amp; to cleaue vnto the Lord that doth thus pitie you in praing
<pb facs="tcp:3045:63" rendition="simple:additions"/>
for you, honour you in making choice of you fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> among others, and in gracing you by vouchſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to receiue you as pledges of his fathers loue, and accounting you as his own. I cannot propone a more forcible motiue to ſtir vp and quicken your hearts to a ſad &amp; ſerious thankfulnes, then to put you in minde that you certaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly are the people that <hi>Chriſt</hi> hath praied for, euen you I meane, the faithfull of this Land and ſtate; who haue ſought the Lord in ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceritie and hearty deuotion. And that I may not now in the Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue of this my weake endeuour ſend you farre backe: I ſhal deſire you to looke, and with open and diſplaied eies, beholde the louing kindenes of the Lord toward our kingdome and countrie, euen in the memory &amp; view of our whole
<pb facs="tcp:3045:64"/>
nation and all Chriſtendome. How eſcaped we the furious and miſcheeuous complotments of manie weightie and malitious deadly enemies in all the peacea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble raigne, &amp; moſt happie and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer enough admired gouernment of that deere Lady, our late ſoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raine Qu. <hi>Elizabeth</hi> of pretious memorie? Did not <hi>Chriſt</hi> pray for vs when all thoſe ſecret deſigne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, popiſh thunder, Cardinal conſpiracies, <hi>Ieſuiticall</hi> proiects, and domeſticall treacheries were diſcouered, &amp; ſet vpon the ſtage? Did not <hi>Chriſt</hi> pray for vs when our ſtate tottered at the deceaſe of our late Soueraigne, and to the wonder of al the Chriſtian world, did as an earthquake ſhake &amp; ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle in a moment? when all na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions about vs ſtood looking at the things likely to enſue?</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:3045:64" rendition="simple:additions"/>What fruſtrated the Popiſh prophecie of <hi>Worthing to<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> the <hi>Ieſuit,</hi> when foreſpeaking as he (hiſpani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olized traitor) wiſhed, <hi>That the fall of one Ladie would be the raiſing of an other.</hi> Meaning that the death of <hi>Ladie Elizabeth</hi> would bee the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>adem of <hi>Izabella Infanta Eugenia Clara?</hi> who brought to ſcorne al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo the ſurmiſe of <hi>Weſton</hi> the <hi>Ieſuite,</hi> another falſe prophet, who ſeeing his fellow <hi>Worthingto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s</hi> ſpel take no effect, went on, and tooke longer time, as the manner of bankrupts is; and ſaid, <hi>That the ſinnes of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland were not ripe at the death of</hi>
               <note place="margin">Weſton de tripl. offic.</note> 
               <hi>Queen Elizabeth. But when England had fulfilled the meaſure of her ſinnes as the Ammorites did, then would the Lord vtterly deſtroy vs.</hi> Which<note place="margin">Gen. 15. 16</note> prophecie of his doubtl<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the powder Treaſon, which if it had beene effected, then had
<pb facs="tcp:3045:65"/>
               <hi>Weſton</hi> deſerued to haue been no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified with a red letter in the liſt of <hi>Anabaptiſticall</hi> prophets. But then euen then alſo Chriſt Ieſus praied for vs, and <hi>Worthington</hi> with his coopſe-mate <hi>Weſton</hi> are found lyars, and we, our prince and peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple are maruellouſly, and miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſly deliuered from the ſulphu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous blaſt complotted at <hi>Rome,</hi> proiected at <hi>Rhemes,</hi> fortified at <hi>Doway,</hi> practiſed in <hi>England,</hi> yea and that which was ſome certain yeeres in intendment and purpoſe was fruſtrated in a moment. Oh then ſeeing not onely the whole land but euen the very particular perſon here preſent can capitulat <hi>in ſpecie,</hi> what great things the Lord hath done for them, where in we now reioice; let it be ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient for me to commemorate in generall, and for euerie one of vs
<pb facs="tcp:3045:65" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>in indiuiduo,</hi> to commune with his owne heart, and write this leſſon there, with the pen of a Diamond that neither day nor night, tide nor time, weale nor woe may ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>literate or blot out the charac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of his diuine leſſon, and ange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licall conſolation, but reſolue that our whole life bee a deuoted ſacrifice of thankfulnes &amp; ſeruice to the liuing God of eternal ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie, through <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> our faithful interceſſor, to whom with God the father, &amp; God the ſanc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifying ſpirit, be rendred al power praiſe, might, and maieſtie this day and euermore. Amen.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The very God of peace ſanctifie you</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Theſ. 5. 23.</note> 
               <hi>throughout, and I pray God that your ſpirits, ſoules and bodies may bee kept blameles vnto ſaluation, through Chriſt Ieſus, this day and euermore.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:3045:66"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3045:66" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
